<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mqtt | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/categories/mqtt/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/"/>
  <updated>2018-04-27T15:10:58+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenWhisk and MQTT]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2016/06/15/openwhisk-and-mqtt/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-15T15:35:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2016/06/15/openwhisk-and-mqtt</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/packages.md#creating-and-using-trigger-feeds">OpenWhisk Feeds</a>
provide the mechanism to bind external events sources to serverless function
executions.</p>

<p><em><strong>Want to use OpenWhisk to listen for database updates to generate usage
statistics? Or write Slack bots that respond to trigger words? Or notify users
when Github project changes?</strong></em></p>

<p>Rather than manually listening for these events with an external application
and calling OpenWhisk <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/actions.md">Actions</a>
through the API, OpenWhisk Feeds automate connecting external events sources with Actions.</p>

<p>Feeds allow users to register
<a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/triggers_rules.md">Triggers</a>
to be invoked when external events occur. Defining
<a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/triggers_rules.md">Rules</a>
that bind these Triggers to Actions, we can have Actions run for external events.</p>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/master/docs/OpenWhisk.png"></p>

<h2>OpenWhisk Packages </h2>

<p>Feeds are contained within and accessible through <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/packages.md">Packages</a>.</p>

<p>OpenWhisk provides numerous built-in packages under the <em>whisk.system</em> namespace.
These packages contain both public Actions and Feeds.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk package list /whisk.system
packages
/whisk.system/alarms                                              shared
/whisk.system/cloudant                                            shared
/whisk.system/watson                                              shared
/whisk.system/system                                              shared
/whisk.system/weather                                             shared
/whisk.system/util                                                shared
/whisk.system/slack                                               shared
/whisk.system/samples                                             shared
/whisk.system/github
</code></p>

<p>Retrieving the package summary, the Actions and Feeds contained within are
returned. Feeds are referenced by the publisher's namespace, package and feed name, e.g.
<em>/whisk.system/alarms/alarm</em></p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk package get /whisk.system/alarms --summary
package /whisk.system/alarms: Alarms and periodic utility
   (params: cron trigger_payload)
 feed   /whisk.system/alarms/alarm: Fire trigger when alarm occurs
</code></p>

<p>The Alarm package (<em>/whisk.system/alarms</em>) contains a single Feed
(<em>/whisk.system/alarms/alarm</em>) that calls the registered Trigger on a fixed
schedule. Users provide the timer schedule through the cron parameter.</p>

<p>When creating new Triggers, users can specify a Feed source to bind their new
Trigger to the external event source. Parameters from the command-line will be
passed to the Feed source. The Feed provider will execute the Trigger each time
an external event occurs.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk trigger create everySecond --feed /whisk.system/alarms/alarm -p cron '*/1 * * * * *' -p trigger_payload '{"vote":"Bernie"}'
</code></p>

<p>This new Trigger will be invoked every second with the payload contents by the
alarm Feed. Using rules, the Feed Trigger can be bound to call an Action on
each invocation.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk rule create --enable alarmRule everySecond actionName
</code></p>

<p><em>As well as using the built-in Feeds, users can create and register custom
Feeds. This provides a way to integrate almost any external event source into
the platform. Publishing custom Feeds within a public package will also make
this event source available to all users on the systen, provided they know the
package identifier.</em></p>

<h2>Creating Custom Feeds</h2>

<p>Users register new Feeds by providing a custom Action to the platform. This
Action is invoked each time the Feed is bound to a new Trigger. Authentication
credentials, supporting Trigger invocation through the OpenWhisk API, are
passed in as invocation parameters.</p>

<p>This sample Action contains an outline for processing requests.</p>

<p>``` javascript Feed Action
// params.lifeCycleEvent - Enum value (CREATE|DELETE)
// params.triggerName - User's Trigger identifier to call
// params.authKey - Authentication details for calling Trigger</p>

<p>function main (params) {
  if (params.lifecycleEvent === 'CREATE') {</p>

<pre><code>create(params);
</code></pre>

<p>  } else if (params.lifecycleEvent === 'DELETE') {</p>

<pre><code>remove(params)
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  return whisk.async();
}
```</p>

<p>The <em>params</em> argument contains the Trigger information provided by the
platform and any parameters from the user during creation.</p>

<p>The <em>lifeCycleEvent</em> parameter is a string value, informing the Feed provider
whether to register (CREATE) or remove (DELETE) the user's Trigger with the
event source.  The Trigger identifier is passed as the <em>triggerName</em> parameter,
with the authentication key (<em>authKey</em>) used for the API requests.</p>

<p>Feed Actions must be registered with a custom annotation (<em>feed</em>), allowing the
platform to distinguish them from "normal" Actions. This annotation can be set
during the create command.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk action create -a feed true feed_name feed_action.js
</code></p>

<p>Once a custom Feed Action has been registered, users can create new Triggers
using that Feed source, following the steps above.</p>

<h2>MQTT Feeds</h2>

<p>The <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_of_things">"Internet of Things"</a>
is often cited as a common usecase for serverless
platforms. Solutions are often event-driven and stateless, e.g. wait for data
from this device, do some processing and then store the results in this
database.</p>

<p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/MQTT">MQTT</a> is a lightweight publish-subscribe
messaging protocol, commonly used for edge of network device-to-device
communication.</p>

<p>Bridging MQTT messages to OpenWhisk Actions can be achieved by creating a new
Feed provider. This provider would subscribe to message topics and execute
registered Triggers with incoming messages.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed/tree/master/provider">custom feed provider</a>
would need to establish and maintain long-lived MQTT
connections, waiting for messages to arrive. This requirements means the Feed
provider needs an external service to handle managing these connections, it
won't be possible within the Feed Action.</p>

<p>This <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed">feed provider service</a> is implemented using Node.js, using Cloudant for the
database. The service listens for HTTP requests, with Trigger registration
details, from the <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed/blob/master/provider/index.js">Feed Action</a>.
The Node.js <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/mqtt">MQTT library</a> is used to subscribe to
registered topics. When messages are received, the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/openwhisk">OpenWhisk client library</a> is
used to invoke the Trigger remotely, passing the message contents as event parameters.</p>

<p>This service provider is <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed/blob/master/provider/Dockerfile">packaged using Docker</a>.</p>

<p>Pushing this image into the <a href="https://console.ng.bluemix.net/docs/containers/container_index.html">IBM Containers registry</a>,
the Feed provider can be started on IBM Bluemix using the Containers service.</p>

<p><code>sh Pushing feed provider to IBM Containers
$ docker build -t USERNAME/mqtt_feed_provider .
$ docker tag USERNAME/mqtt_feed_provider registry.ng.bluemix.net/USERNAME/mqtt_feed_provider
$ docker push registry.ng.bluemix.net/USERNAME/mqtt_feed_provider
</code></p>

<p><img src="/images/create_container.png"></p>

<h2>Registering Feeds</h2>

<p>With the Feed service provider running, the Feed Action can be deployed.</p>

<p>The Feed will be registered under the name, <em>mqtt_feed_provider</em>, in a custom
package, mqtt.</p>

<p>Using the <em>--shared</em> command-line flag, the Feed package can be registered as a
public package. Feeds and Actions within public packages are visible to every
system user.</p>

<p>Rather than hardcoding the service provider location within the Feed Action,
this configuration value will be accessible as a package parameter. This can be
updated at runtime with modifying the Feed Action source.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk package create --shared -p provider_endpoint "http://CONTAINER_IP:3000/mqtt" mqtt
$ wsk package update mqtt -a description 'MQTT topic feed. Messages received on broker topic as passed to triggers"
</code></p>

<p>Having created the package, we can add the Feed Action, using the custom
attribute to denote this is a Feed Action.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk action create -a feed true mqtt/mqtt_feed mqtt_feed.js
</code></p>

<p>Once the Feed has been registered, it can be referenced when creating new Triggers.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk trigger create feed_trigger --feed /james.thomas@uk.ibm.com_dev/mqtt/mqtt_feed -p topic 'whiskers' -p url 'mqtt://test.mosca.io'
</code></p>

<p>MQTT broker url and topic name are passed as Trigger parameters, using the -p
flags. These values are included within the invocation arguments to the Feed
Action, shown below.</p>

<p><code>javascript
var params = {
  authKey: 'USERNAME:PASSWORD',
  url: 'mqtt://test.mosca.io',
  provider_endpoint: 'http://CONTAINER_IP:3000/mqtt',
  topic: 'whiskers',
  lifecycleEvent: 'CREATE',
  triggerName: '/james.thomas@uk.ibm.com_dev/feed_trigger'
}
</code></p>

<p>Once the Feed service provider has connected to the broker and subscribed to
the topic, incoming messages will register as Trigger events invocations for
the public_feed Trigger.</p>

<p>Using this custom Feed, users can easily connect MQTT messages to OpenWhisk Actions.</p>

<h2>Github Project</h2>

<p>Source code for this custom OpenWhisk Feed is available <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed">here</a>.
The project contains the <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed/blob/master/feed_action.js">Feed Action</a>
and <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed/tree/master/provider">Provider service</a>.
The <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_mqtt_feed/blob/master/README.md">README</a> contains the deployment and usage instructions.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
