<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: tensorflow | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/categories/tensorflow/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/"/>
  <updated>2018-08-07T09:56:54+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Machine Learning In Node.js With TensorFlow.js]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2018/08/07/machine-learning-in-node-dot-js-with-tensorflow-dot-js/"/>
    <updated>2018-08-07T09:52:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2018/08/07/machine-learning-in-node-dot-js-with-tensorflow-dot-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/">TensorFlow.js</a> is a new version of the popular open-source library which brings deep learning to JavaScript. Developers can now define, train, and run machine learning models using the <a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/api/0.12.0/">high-level library API</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/">Pre-trained models</a> mean developers can now easily perform complex tasks like <a href="https://emojiscavengerhunt.withgoogle.com/">visual recognition</a>, <a href="https://magenta.tensorflow.org/demos/performance_rnn/index.html#2|2,0,1,0,1,1,0,1,0,1,0,1|1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1|1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1,1|false">generating music</a> or <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/demos/posenet/camera.html">detecting human poses</a> with just a few lines of JavaScript.</p>

<p>Having started as a front-end library for web browsers, recent updates added <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-node">experimental support</a> for Node.js. This allows TensorFlow.js to be used in backend JavaScript applications without having to use Python.</p>

<p><em>Reading about the library, I wanted to test it out with a simple task...</em> 🧐</p>

<blockquote><p> <strong>Use TensorFlow.js to perform visual recognition on images using JavaScript from Node.js</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>Unfortunately, most of the <a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/#getting-started">documentation</a> and <a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/tutorials/webcam-transfer-learning.html">example code</a> provided uses the library in a browser. <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/mobilenet">Project utilities</a> provided to simplify loading and using pre-trained models have not yet been extended with Node.js support. Getting this working did end up with me spending a lot of time reading the Typescript source files for the library. 👎</p>

<p>However, after a few days' hacking, I managed to get <a href="https://gist.github.com/jthomas/145610bdeda2638d94fab9a397eb1f1d">this completed</a>! Hurrah! 🤩</p>

<p><em>Before we dive into the code, let's start with an overview of the different TensorFlow libraries.</em></p>

<h2>TensorFlow</h2>

<p><a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/">TensorFlow</a> is an open-source software library for machine learning applications. TensorFlow can be used to implement neural networks and other deep learning algorithms.</p>

<p>Released by Google in November 2015, TensorFlow was originally a <a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/api_docs/python/">Python library</a>. It used either CPU or GPU-based computation for training and evaluating machine learning models. The library was initially designed to run on high-performance servers with expensive GPUs.</p>

<p>Recent updates have extended the software to run in resource-constrained environments like mobile devices and web browsers.</p>

<h3>TensorFlow Lite</h3>

<p><a href="https://www.tensorflow.org/mobile/tflite/">Tensorflow Lite</a>, a lightweight version of the library for mobile and embedded devices, was released in May 2017. This was accompanied by a new series of pre-trained deep learning models for vision recognition tasks, called <a href="https://ai.googleblog.com/2017/06/mobilenets-open-source-models-for.html">MobileNet</a>. MobileNet models were designed to work efficiently in resource-constrained environments like mobile devices.</p>

<h3>TensorFlow.js</h3>

<p>Following Tensorflow Lite, <a href="https://medium.com/tensorflow/introducing-tensorflow-js-machine-learning-in-javascript-bf3eab376db">TensorFlow.js</a> was announced in March 2018. This version of the library was designed to run in the browser, building on an earlier project called <a href="https://twitter.com/deeplearnjs">deeplearn.js</a>. WebGL provides GPU access to the library. Developers use a JavaScript API to train, load and run models.</p>

<p>TensorFlow.js was recently extended to run on Node.js, using an <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-node">extension library</a> called <code>tfjs-node</code>.</p>

<p><em>The Node.js extension is an alpha release and still under active development.</em></p>

<h4>Importing Existing Models Into TensorFlow.js</h4>

<p>Existing TensorFlow and Keras models can be executed using the TensorFlow.js library. Models need converting to a new format <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-converter">using this tool</a> before execution. Pre-trained and converted models for image classification, pose detection and k-nearest neighbours are <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models">available on Github</a>.</p>

<h2>Using TensorFlow.js in Node.js</h2>

<h3>Installing TensorFlow Libraries</h3>

<p>TensorFlow.js can be installed from the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">NPM registry</a>.</p>

<ul>
<li><code>@tensorflow/tfjs</code> - <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@tensorflow/tfjs">Core TensorFlow.js library</a></li>
<li><code>@tensorflow/tfjs-node</code> - <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@tensorflow/tfjs-node">TensorFlow.js Node.js extension</a></li>
<li><code>@tensorflow/tfjs-node-gpu</code> - <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/@tensorflow/tfjs-node-gpu">TensorFlow.js Node.js extension with GPU support</a></li>
</ul>


<p><code>
npm install @tensorflow/tfjs @tensorflow/tfjs-node
// or...
npm install @tensorflow/tfjs @tensorflow/tfjs-node-gpu
</code></p>

<p>Both Node.js extensions use native dependencies which will be compiled on demand.</p>

<h3>Loading TensorFlow Libraries</h3>

<p>TensorFlow's <a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/api/0.12.0/">JavaScript API</a> is exposed from the core library. Extension modules to enable Node.js support do not expose additional APIs.</p>

<p><code>javascript
const tf = require('@tensorflow/tfjs')
// Load the binding (CPU computation)
require('@tensorflow/tfjs-node')
// Or load the binding (GPU computation)
require('@tensorflow/tfjs-node-gpu')
</code></p>

<h3>Loading TensorFlow Models</h3>

<p>TensorFlow.js provides an <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models">NPM library</a> (<code>tfjs-models</code>) to ease loading pre-trained &amp; converted models for <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/mobilenet">image classification</a>, <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/posenet">pose detection</a> and <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/knn-classifier">k-nearest neighbours</a>.</p>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/mobilenet">MobileNet model</a> used for image classification is a deep neural network trained to <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/imagenet_classes.ts">identify 1000 different classes</a>.</p>

<p>In the project's README, the <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/mobilenet#via-npm">following example code</a> is used to load the model.</p>

<p>```javascript
import * as mobilenet from '@tensorflow-models/mobilenet';</p>

<p>// Load the model.
const model = await mobilenet.load();
```</p>

<p><strong>One of the first challenges I encountered was that this does not work on Node.js.</strong></p>

<p><code>
Error: browserHTTPRequest is not supported outside the web browser.
</code></p>

<p>Looking at the <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/index.ts#L27">source code</a>, the <code>mobilenet</code> library is a wrapper around the underlying <code>tf.Model</code> class. When the <code>load()</code> method is called, it automatically downloads the correct model files from an external HTTP address and instantiates the TensorFlow model.</p>

<p>The Node.js extension does not yet support HTTP requests to dynamically retrieve models. Instead, models must be manually loaded from the filesystem.</p>

<p><em>After reading the source code for the library, I managed to create a work-around...</em></p>

<h4>Loading Models From a Filesystem</h4>

<p>Rather than calling the module's <code>load</code> method, if the <code>MobileNet</code> class is created manually, the auto-generated <code>path</code> variable which contains the HTTP address of the model can be overwritten with a local filesystem path. Having done this, calling the <code>load</code> method on the class instance will trigger the <a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/tutorials/model-save-load.html">filesystem loader class</a>, rather than trying to use the browser-based HTTP loader.</p>

<p><code>javascript
const path = "mobilenet/model.json"
const mn = new mobilenet.MobileNet(1, 1);
mn.path = `file://${path}`
await mn.load()
</code></p>

<p><strong>Awesome, it works!</strong></p>

<p><em>But how where do the models files come from?</em></p>

<h3>MobileNet Models</h3>

<p>Models for TensorFlow.js consist of two file types, a model configuration file stored in JSON and model weights in a binary format. Model weights are often sharded into multiple files for better caching by browsers.</p>

<p>Looking at the <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/index.ts#L68-L76">automatic loading code</a> for MobileNet models, models configuration and weight shards are retrieved from a public storage bucket at this address.</p>

<p><code>
https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/tfjs/mobilenet_v${version}_${alpha}_${size}/
</code></p>

<p>The template parameters in the URL refer to the model versions listed <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/models/blob/master/research/slim/nets/mobilenet_v1.md#pre-trained-models">here</a>. Classification accuracy results for each version are also shown on that page.</p>

<p><em>According to the <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/index.ts#L36">source code</a>, only MobileNet v1 models can be loaded using the <code>tensorflow-models/mobilenet</code> library.</em></p>

<p>The HTTP retrieval code loads the <code>model.json</code> file from this location and then recursively fetches all referenced model weights shards. These files are in the format <code>groupX-shard1of1</code>.</p>

<h4>Downloading Models Manually</h4>

<p>Saving all model files to a filesystem can be achieved by retrieving the model configuration file, parsing out the referenced weight files and downloading each weight file manually.</p>

<p><strong>I want to use the MobileNet V1 Module with 1.0 alpha value and image size of 224 pixels.</strong> This gives me the <a href="https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/tfjs/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224/model.json">following URL</a> for the model configuration file.</p>

<p><code>
https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/tfjs/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224/model.json
</code></p>

<p>Once this file has been downloaded locally, I can use the <a href="https://stedolan.github.io/jq/"><code>jq</code> tool</a> to parse all the weight file names.</p>

<p><code>
$ cat model.json | jq -r ".weightsManifest[].paths[0]"
group1-shard1of1
group2-shard1of1
group3-shard1of1
...
</code></p>

<p>Using the <code>sed</code> tool, I can prefix these names with the HTTP URL to generate URLs for each weight file.</p>

<p><code>
$ cat model.json | jq -r ".weightsManifest[].paths[0]" | sed 's/^/https:\/\/storage.googleapis.com\/tfjs-models\/tfjs\/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224\//'
https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/tfjs/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224/group1-shard1of1
https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/tfjs/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224/group2-shard1of1
https://storage.googleapis.com/tfjs-models/tfjs/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224/group3-shard1of1
...
</code></p>

<p>Using the <code>parallel</code> and <code>curl</code> commands, I can then download all of these files to my local directory.</p>

<p><code>
cat model.json | jq -r ".weightsManifest[].paths[0]" | sed 's/^/https:\/\/storage.googleapis.com\/tfjs-models\/tfjs\/mobilenet_v1_1.0_224\//' |  parallel curl -O
</code></p>

<h3>Classifying Images</h3>

<p><a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/tree/master/mobilenet#via-npm">This example code</a> is provided by TensorFlow.js to demonstrate returning classifications for an image.</p>

<p>```javascript
const img = document.getElementById('img');</p>

<p>// Classify the image.
const predictions = await model.classify(img);
```</p>

<p><strong>This does not work on Node.js due to the lack of a DOM.</strong></p>

<p>The <code>classify</code> <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/index.ts#L143-L155">method</a> accepts numerous DOM elements (<code>canvas</code>, <code>video</code>, <code>image</code>) and will automatically retrieve and convert image bytes from these elements into a <a href="https://js.tensorflow.org/api/latest/index.html#tensor3d"><code>tf.Tensor3D</code> class</a> which is used as the input to the model. Alternatively, the <code>tf.Tensor3D</code> input can be passed directly.</p>

<p><strong>Rather than trying to use an external package to simulate a DOM element in Node.js, I found it easier to construct the <code>tf.Tensor3D</code> manually.</strong></p>

<h4>Generating Tensor3D from an Image</h4>

<p>Reading the <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-core/blob/master/src/kernels/backend_cpu.ts#L126-L140">source code</a> for the method used to turn DOM elements into Tensor3D classes, the following input parameters are used to generate the Tensor3D class.</p>

<p><code>javascript
const values = new Int32Array(image.height * image.width * numChannels);
// fill pixels with pixel channel bytes from image
const outShape = [image.height, image.width, numChannels];
const input = tf.tensor3d(values, outShape, 'int32');
</code></p>

<p><code>pixels</code> is a 2D array of type (Int32Array) which contains a sequential list of channel values for each pixel. <code>numChannels</code> is the number of channel values per pixel.</p>

<h4>Creating Input Values For JPEGs</h4>

<p>The <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/jpeg-js"><code>jpeg-js</code> library</a> is a pure javascript JPEG encoder and decoder for Node.js. Using this library the RGB values for each pixel can be extracted.</p>

<p><code>javascript
const pixels = jpeg.decode(buffer, true);
</code></p>

<p>This will return a <code>Uint8Array</code> with four channel values (<code>RGBA</code>) for each pixel (<code>width * height</code>). The MobileNet model only uses the three colour channels (<code>RGB</code>) for classification, ignoring the alpha channel. This code converts the four channel array into the correct three channel version.</p>

<p>```javascript
const numChannels = 3;
const numPixels = image.width * image.height;
const values = new Int32Array(numPixels * numChannels);</p>

<p>for (let i = 0; i &lt; numPixels; i++) {
  for (let channel = 0; channel &lt; numChannels; ++channel) {</p>

<pre><code>values[i * numChannels + channel] = pixels[i * 4 + channel];
</code></pre>

<p>  }
}
```</p>

<h4>MobileNet Models Input Requirements</h4>

<p>The <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/models/blob/master/research/slim/nets/mobilenet_v1.md#mobilenet_v1">MobileNet model</a> being used classifies images of width and height 224 pixels. Input tensors must contain float values, between -1 and 1, for each of the three channels pixel values.</p>

<p>Input values for images of different dimensions needs to be re-sized before classification. Additionally, pixels values from the JPEG decoder are in the range <em>0 - 255</em>, rather than <em>-1 to 1</em>. These values also need converting prior to classification.</p>

<p><strong>TensorFlow.js has library methods to make this process easier but, fortunately for us, the <code>tfjs-models/mobilenet</code> library <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/index.ts#L103-L114">automatically handles</a> this issue!</strong> 👍</p>

<p>Developers can pass in Tensor3D inputs of type <code>int32</code>  and different dimensions to the  <code>classify</code> method and it converts the input to the correct format prior to classification. Which means there's nothing to do... Super 🕺🕺🕺.</p>

<h4>Obtaining Predictions</h4>

<p>MobileNet models in Tensorflow are trained to recognise entities from the <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/imagenet_classes.ts">top 1000 classes</a> in the <a href="http://image-net.org/">ImageNet</a> dataset. The models output the probabilities that each of those entities is in the image being classified.</p>

<p><em>The full list of trained classes for the model being used can be found in <a href="https://github.com/tensorflow/tfjs-models/blob/master/mobilenet/src/imagenet_classes.ts">this file</a>.</em></p>

<p>The <code>tfjs-models/mobilenet</code> library exposes a <code>classify</code> method on the <code>MobileNet</code> class to return the top X classes with highest probabilities from an image input.</p>

<p><code>javascript
const predictions = await mn_model.classify(input, 10);
</code></p>

<p><code>predictions</code> is an array of X classes and probabilities in the following format.</p>

<p><code>javascript
{
  className: 'panda',
  probability: 0.9993536472320557
}
</code></p>

<h2>Example</h2>

<p>Having worked how to use the TensorFlow.js library and MobileNet models on Node.js, <a href="https://gist.github.com/jthomas/145610bdeda2638d94fab9a397eb1f1d">this script</a> will classify an image given as a command-line argument.</p>

<h3>source code</h3>

<ul>
<li>Save this script file and package descriptor to local files.</li>
</ul>


<script src="https://gist.github.com/jthomas/145610bdeda2638d94fab9a397eb1f1d.js"></script>


<h3>testing it out</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>Download the model files to a <code>mobilenet</code> directory using the instructions above.</p></li>
<li><p>Install the project dependencies using NPM
<code>
npm install
</code></p></li>
<li><p>Download a sample JPEG file to classify
<code>
wget http://bit.ly/2JYSal9 -O panda.jpg
</code>
<img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/f/fe/Giant_Panda_in_Beijing_Zoo_1.JPG"></p></li>
<li><p>Run the script with the model file and input image as arguments.
<code>
node script.js mobilenet/model.json panda.jpg
</code></p></li>
</ul>


<p><strong>If everything worked, the following output should be printed to the console.</strong></p>

<p>```javascript
classification results: [ {</p>

<pre><code>className: 'giant panda, panda, panda bear, coon bear',
probability: 0.9993536472320557 
</code></pre>

<p>} ]
```</p>

<p>The image is correctly classified as containing a Panda with 99.93% probability! 🐼🐼🐼</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>TensorFlow.js brings the power of deep learning to JavaScript developers. Using pre-trained models with the TensorFlow.js library makes it simple to extend JavaScript applications with complex machine learning tasks with minimal effort and code.</p>

<p>Having been released as a browser-based library, TensorFlow.js has now been extended to work on Node.js, although not all of the tools and utilities support the new runtime. With a few days' hacking, I was able to use the library with the MobileNet models for visual recognition on images from a local file.</p>

<p>Getting this working in the Node.js runtime means I now move on to my next idea... making this run inside a serverless function! Come back soon to read about my next adventure with TensorFlow.js. 👋</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
