<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: python | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/categories/python/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/"/>
  <updated>2018-01-22T17:08:15+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Large Applications on OpenWhisk]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2017/08/04/large-applications-on-openwhisk/"/>
    <updated>2017-08-04T09:48:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2017/08/04/large-applications-on-openwhisk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenWhisk supports <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/docs/actions.md#packaging-an-action-as-a-nodejs-module">creating actions from archive files</a> containing source files and project dependencies.</p>

<p><blockquote><p>The maximum code size for the action is 48MB.</p><footer><strong>OpenWhisk system details,</strong> <cite><a href='https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/docs/reference.md#per-action-artifact-mb-fixed-48mb'>github.com/apache/blob/master/&hellip;</a></cite></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>Applications with lots of third-party modules, native libraries or external tools may be soon find themselves running into this limit. Node.js libraries are <a href="https://medium.com/friendship-dot-js/i-peeked-into-my-node-modules-directory-and-you-wont-believe-what-happened-next-b89f63d21558">notorious for having large amounts of dependencies</a>.</p>

<p><em>What if you need to deploy an application larger than this limit to OpenWhisk?</em></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/tree/master/sdk/docker">Previous solutions</a> used Docker support in OpenWhisk to build a custom Docker image per action. Source files and dependencies are built into a public image hosted on Docker Hub.</p>

<p>This approach overcomes the limit on deployment size but means application source files will be accessible on Docker Hub. This is not an issue for building samples or open-source projects but not realistic for most applications.</p>

<p><em>So, using an application larger than this limit requires me to make my source files public?</em> 🤔</p>

<p><strong>There's now a better solution!</strong> 👏👏👏</p>

<p><strong>OpenWhisk supports creating actions from an archive file AND a custom Docker image.</strong></p>

<p>If we build a custom Docker runtime which includes shared libraries, those dependencies don't need including in the archive file. Private source files will still be bundled in the archive and injected at runtime.</p>

<p>Reducing archive file sizes also improves deployment times.</p>

<p><em>Let's look at an example…</em></p>

<h2>Using Machine Learning Libraries on OpenWhisk</h2>

<p>Python is a popular language for machine learning and data science. Libraries like <a href="http://pandas.pydata.org/">pandas</a>, <a href="http://scikit-learn.org/stable/">scikit-learn</a> and <a href="http://www.numpy.org/">numpy</a> provide all the tools. Serverless computing is becoming a <a href="https://blog.alexcasalboni.com/serverless-computing-machine-learning-baf52b89e1b0">good choice for machine learning microservices</a>.</p>

<p>OpenWhisk supports <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/docs/actions.md#creating-python-actions">Python 2 and 3 runtimes</a>.</p>

<p>Popular libraries like flask, requests and beautifulsoup <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/docs/reference.md#python-actions">are available as global packages</a>. Additional packages can be imported using <code>virutalenv</code> during invocations.</p>

<h3>Python Machine Learning Libraries</h3>

<p>Python packages can be <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/04/27/python-packages-in-openwhisk/">used in OpenWhisk using virtualenv</a>. Developers install the packages locally and include the <code>virutalenv</code> folder in the archive for deployment.</p>

<p>Machine Learning libraries often use numerous shared libraries and compile native dependencies for performance. <strong>This can lead to hundreds of megabytes of dependencies.</strong></p>

<p>Setting up a new <code>virtualenv</code> folder and installing <code>pandas</code> leads to an environment with nearly 100MB of dependencies.</p>

<p><code>
$ virtualenv env
$ source env/bin/activate
$ pip install pandas
...
Installing collected packages: numpy, six, python-dateutil, pytz, pandas
Successfully installed numpy-1.13.1 pandas-0.20.3 python-dateutil-2.6.1 pytz-2017.2 six-1.10.0
$ du -h
...
84M . &lt;-- FOLDER SIZE 😱
</code></p>

<p><strong>Bundling these libraries within an archive file will not be possible due to the file size limit.</strong></p>

<h3>Custom OpenWhisk Runtime Images</h3>

<p>Overcoming this limit can be achieved using a custom runtime image. The runtime will pre-install additional libraries during the build process and make them available during invocations.</p>

<p>OpenWhisk uses <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> for the runtime containers. <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/tree/master/core">Source files for the images</a> are available on Github under the <code>core</code> folder. Here's the <code>Dockerfile</code> for the Python runtime: <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/core/pythonAction/Dockerfile">https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/core/pythonAction/Dockerfile</a>.</p>

<p>Images for OpenWhisk runtimes are also available on Docker Hub under the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/openwhisk/">OpenWhisk organisation</a>.</p>

<p><em>Docker supports building new images from a parent image using the <code>FROM</code> directive. Inheriting from the existing runtime images means the <code>Dockerfile</code> for the new runtime only has to contain commands for installing extra dependencies.</em></p>

<p>Let's build a new Python runtime which includes those libraries as shared packages.</p>

<h3>Building Runtimes</h3>

<p>Let's create a new <code>Dockerfile</code> which installs additional packages into the OpenWhisk Python runtime.</p>

<p>```
FROM openwhisk/python3action</p>

<h1>lapack-dev is available in community repo.</h1>

<p>RUN echo "http://dl-4.alpinelinux.org/alpine/edge/community" >> /etc/apk/repositories</p>

<h1>add package build dependencies</h1>

<p>RUN apk add --no-cache \</p>

<pre><code>    g++ \
    lapack-dev \
    gfortran
</code></pre>

<h1>add python packages</h1>

<p>RUN pip install \</p>

<pre><code>numpy \
pandas \
scipy \
sklearn
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Running the <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/commandline/build/">Docker build command</a> will create a new image with these extra dependencies.</p>

<p><code>
$ docker build -t python_ml_runtime .
Sending build context to Docker daemon  83.01MB
Step 1/4 : FROM openwhisk/python3action
 ---&gt; 46388e726fae
...
Successfully built cfc14a93863e
Successfully tagged python_ml_runtime:latest
</code></p>

<p><em>Hosting images on Docker Hub requires registering a (free) account @ https://hub.docker.com/</em></p>

<p>Create a new tag from the <code>python_ml_runtime</code> image containing the Docker Hub username.</p>

<p><code>
$ docker tag python_ml_runtime &lt;YOUR_USERNAME&gt;/python_ml_test
</code></p>

<p>Push the image to Docker Hub to make it available to OpenWhisk.</p>

<p><code>
$ docker push &lt;YOUR_USERNAME&gt;/python_ml_test
</code></p>

<h3>Testing It Out</h3>

<p>Create a new Python file (<code>main.py</code>) with the following contents:</p>

<p>```python
import numpy
import pandas
import sklearn
import scipy</p>

<p>def main(params):</p>

<pre><code>return {
    "numpy": numpy.__version__,
    "pandas": pandas.__version__,
    "sklearn": sklearn.__version__,
    "scipy": scipy.__version__
}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Create a new OpenWhisk action using the Docker image from above and source file.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk action create lib-versions --docker &lt;YOUR_USERNAME&gt;/openwhisk_python_ml main.py
ok: created action lib-versions
</code></p>

<p> Invoke the action to verify the modules are available and return the versions.</p>

<p>```
$ wsk action invoke lib-versions --result
{</p>

<pre><code>"numpy": "1.13.1",
"pandas": "0.20.3",
"scipy": "0.19.1",
"sklearn": "0.18.2"
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Yass. It works. 💃🕺</p>

<p>Serverless Machine Learning here we come…. 😉</p>

<h2>Conclusions</h2>

<p>Using custom runtimes with private source files is an amazing feature of OpenWhisk. It enables developers to run larger applications on the platform but also enables lots of other use cases. <strong>Almost any runtime, library or tool can now be used from the platform.</strong></p>

<p>Here are some examples of where this approach could be used…</p>

<ul>
<li><em>Installing global libraries to reduce archive file size under 48MB and speed up deployments.</em></li>
<li><em>Upgrading language runtimes, i.e. using Node.js 8 instead of 6.</em></li>
<li><em>Adding native dependencies or command-line tools to the environment, e.g. ffmpeg.</em></li>
</ul>


<p>Building new runtimes is really simple using pre-existing base images published on Dockerhub.</p>

<p><strong>The possibilities are endless!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Python Packages in OpenWhisk]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2017/04/27/python-packages-in-openwhisk/"/>
    <updated>2017-04-27T17:15:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2017/04/27/python-packages-in-openwhisk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>OpenWhisk's Python runtime <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/reference.md#python-actions">includes popular third-party libraries</a> like requests, scrapy and simplejson. Developers don't have to manually install packages to use those libraries.</p>

<p><em>Great, but what about using other libraries that aren't pre-installed?</em></p>

<p>In a <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/11/28/npm-modules-in-openwhisk/">previous blog post</a>, we showed how to deploy Node.js actions from zip files containing third-party modules. These modules are then made available in the Node.js runtime.</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/pull/1940">Recent updates</a> to OpenWhisk allow us to use the same approach with the Python runtime!</strong></p>

<h2>Python Packages</h2>

<p>Python packages can be installed using the <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pip">pip tool</a>. This can be used to install individual packages or a series of dependencies from an external file.</p>

<p><code>
$ pip install blah
$ pip install -r requirements.txt
</code></p>

<p>pip defaults to installing packages in a global location (<a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/31384639/what-is-pythons-site-packages-directory">site-packages</a>) which is shared between all users. This can cause issues when different projects require different versions of the same package.</p>

<h3>virtualenv</h3>

<p><a href="http://python-guide-pt-br.readthedocs.io/en/latest/dev/virtualenvs/">virtualenv</a> is a tool that solves this issue by creating virtual python environments for projects. The virtual environment includes a custom <code>site-packages</code> folder to install packages into.</p>

<p><code>
$ virtualenv env
Using base prefix '/Library/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/3.6'
New python executable in /private/tmp/env/bin/python3.6
Also creating executable in /private/tmp/env/bin/python
Installing setuptools, pip, wheel...done.
</code></p>

<p>OpenWhisk <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/pull/1940">recently added support</a> for using virtualenv in the Python runtime.</p>

<h3>custom packages on openwhisk</h3>

<p>OpenWhisk actions can be created from a zip file <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/actions.md#packaging-an-action-as-a-nodejs-module">containing source files and other resources</a>.</p>

<p>If the archive includes a virtual Python environment folder, the platform runs the <code>./bin/activate_this.py</code> script before executing Python actions. This script modifies the module search path to include the local <code>site-packages</code> folder.</p>

<p><em>This will only happen during "cold" activations.</em></p>

<p><strong>This feature comes with the following restrictions.</strong></p>

<ul>
<li>Virtual Python environment must be in a folder called <code>virtualenv</code> under the top-level directory.</li>
<li>Packages must be available for the Python runtime being used in OpenWhisk (2.7 or 3.6).</li>
</ul>


<p>Let's look at an example of building an OpenWhisk Python action which uses an external Python package.</p>

<h3>Python Package Example</h3>

<p>The <a href="https://pypi.python.org/pypi/pyjokes">pyjokes</a> package provides a library for generating (terrible) jokes for programmers. Let's turn this package into an API (Jokes-as-a-Service!) using the Python runtime on OpenWhisk.</p>

<p>Start by creating a new directory for your project and set up the virtual Python environment.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ mkdir jokes; cd jokes
$ virtualenv virtualenv
Using base prefix '/Library/Frameworks/Python.framework/Versions/3.6'
New python executable in /tmp/jokes/virtualenv/bin/python3.6
Also creating executable in /tmp/jokes/virtualenv/bin/python
Installing setuptools, pip, wheel...done.
$ source virtualenv/bin/activate
(virtualenv) $ pip install pyjokes
Collecting pyjokes
  Using cached pyjokes-0.5.0-py2.py3-none-any.whl
Installing collected packages: pyjokes
Successfully installed pyjokes-0.5.0
(virtualenv) $
</code></p>

<p>In the project directory, create a new file (<code>__main__.py</code>) and paste the following code.</p>

<p>```python
import pyjokes</p>

<p>def joke(params):</p>

<pre><code>return {"joke": pyjokes.get_joke()}
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<p>Check the script works with the Python intepreter.</p>

<p>```sh
(virtualenv) $ python -i .</p>

<blockquote><blockquote><blockquote><p>joke({})
{'joke': 'What do you call a programmer from Finland? Nerdic.'}</p>

<p>```</p></blockquote></blockquote></blockquote>

<p>Add the <code>virtualenv</code> folder and Python script to a new zip file.</p>

<p><code>
$ zip -r jokes.zip virtualenv __main__.py
  adding: virtualenv/ (stored 0%)
  adding: virtualenv/.Python (deflated 65%)
  adding: virtualenv/bin/ (stored 0%)
  adding: virtualenv/bin/activate (deflated 63%)
  ...
$ ls
__main__.py  jokes.zip   virtualenv
</code></p>

<p>Create a new OpenWhisk action for the Python runtime using the <code>wsk</code> cli.</p>

<p><code>
$ wsk action create jokes --kind python:3 --main joke jokes.zip
ok: created action jokes
</code></p>

<p>Invoking our new action will return (bad) jokes on-demand using the third-party Python package.</p>

<p>```
$ wsk action invoke jokes --blocking --result
{</p>

<pre><code>"joke": "Software salesmen and used-car salesmen differ in that the latter know when they are lying."
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<h3>Installing Packages With Docker</h3>

<p>In the example above, the Python runtime used in development (v3.6) matched the OpenWhisk runtime environment. Packages installed using <code>virtualenv</code> must be for the same major and minor versions of the Python runtime used by OpenWhisk.</p>

<p>OpenWhisk publishes the runtime environments as <a href="https://hub.docker.com/u/openwhisk/">Docker images on Docker Hub</a>.</p>

<p>Running containers from <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/openwhisk/python3action/">those runtime images</a> provides a way to download packages for the correct environment.</p>

<p><code>
$ docker run --rm -v "$PWD:/tmp" openwhisk/python3action sh \
  -c "cd tmp; virtualenv virtualenv; source virtualenv/bin/activate; pip install pyjokes;"
Using base prefix '/usr/local'
New python executable in /tmp/virtualenv/bin/python3.6
Also creating executable in /tmp/virtualenv/bin/python
Installing setuptools, pip, wheel...done.
Collecting pyjokes
  Downloading pyjokes-0.5.0-py2.py3-none-any.whl
Installing collected packages: pyjokes
Successfully installed pyjokes-0.5.0
$
</code></p>

<p>This will leave you a <code>virtualenv</code> folder in the current directory with packages for the correct Python runtime.</p>

<h3>Speeding Up Deployments</h3>

<p>Peeking inside the <code>virtualenv</code> folder reveals a huge number of files to set up the virtual Python environment. If we just want to use a third-party package from the local <code>site-packages</code> folder, most of those files are unnecessary.</p>

<p><em>Adding this entire folder to the zip archive will unnecessarily inflate the file size. This will slow down deployments and increase execution time for cold activations. OpenWhisk also has a maximum size for action source code of 48MB.</em></p>

<p>Manually including individual <code>site-packages</code> folders, rather than the entire <code>virtualenv</code> directory, will ensure the archive file only contains packages being used. We must also add the Python script (<code>virtualenv/bin/activate_this.py</code>) executed by OpenWhisk to modify the module search path.</p>

<p><code>
$ zip -r jokes_small.zip virtualenv/bin/activate_this.py virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes __main__.py
updating: virtualenv/bin/activate_this.py (deflated 54%)
updating: virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/ (stored 0%)
updating: virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/__init__.py (deflated 20%)
updating: virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/jokes_de.py (deflated 29%)
updating: virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/jokes_en.py (deflated 61%)
updating: virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/jokes_es.py (deflated 40%)
updating: virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/pyjokes.py (deflated 68%)
updating: __main__.py (deflated 18%)
$ ls -lh
total 40984
-rw-r--r--  1 james  wheel    74B 21 Apr 11:01 __main__.py
-rw-r--r--  1 james  wheel    20M 21 Apr 11:07 jokes.zip
-rw-r--r--  1 james  wheel   9.3K 21 Apr 13:36 jokes_small.zip
drwxr-xr-x  6 james  wheel   204B 21 Apr 11:25 virtualenv
</code></p>

<p>The archive file is now less than ten kilobytes! 🏃</p>

<h4>With The Serverless Framework</h4>

<p><a href="https://serverless.com/">The Serverless Framework</a> is a popular open-source framework for building serverless applications. This framework handles the configuration, packaging and deployment of your serverless application.</p>

<p>OpenWhisk is supported through a <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/serverless-openwhisk">provider plugin</a>. <a href="https://medium.com/openwhisk/serverless-framework-and-openwhisk-plugin-update-v0-6-1339cfdcd2d2">Recent versions</a> of the plugin added support for the Python runtime environment.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://serverless.com/framework/docs/providers/openwhisk/guide/serverless.yml/">application configuration file</a> for the framework, users can add <code>include</code> and <code>exclude</code> parameters to control the contents of the archive file before deployment.</p>

<p>Here's an example of the configuration needed to only include the necessary files for the application above.</p>

<p>```yaml
service: pyjokes</p>

<p>provider:
  name: openwhisk
  runtime: python:3</p>

<p>functions:
  jokes:</p>

<pre><code>handler: handler.joke
</code></pre>

<p>plugins:
  - serverless-openwhisk</p>

<p>package:
  exclude:</p>

<pre><code>- virtualenv/**
- '!virtualenv/bin/activate_this.py'
- '!virtualenv/lib/python3.6/site-packages/pyjokes/**'
</code></pre>

<p>```</p>

<h3>conclusion</h3>

<p>Python has a huge community of third-party packages for everything from parsing JSON, making HTTP requests and even generating jokes. OpenWhisk already provided a number of the most popular packages within the Python runtime.</p>

<p>Users can install additional packages locally using the <code>pip</code> and <code>virtualenv</code> tools. Bundling those files within the deployment archive means they are extracted into the OpenWhisk Python runtime environment.</p>

<p>Recent changes to the Python runtime allows the platform to automatically add local package folders to the module search path.</p>

<p><strong>This means Python functions running on OpenWhisk can now use any third-party library as if it was installed globally.</strong></p>

<p>Hurrah 👌!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
