<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>mvc on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/mvc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in mvc on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/mvc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Part 3: Controllers</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/05/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-part-3-controllers/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/05/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-part-3-controllers/</guid>
      <description>In the final article of this series, we&amp;rsquo;ll be looking at creating an MVC Controller for our sample todo application.
We&amp;rsquo;ve already shown how to define our application model, creating a domain-specific todo model backed by localStorage, along with our view template, using widget templating to render our tasks into the page.
 The controller translates user input into operations on the model. Model View Controller Pattern http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93controller Wikipedia
 For our application, we need to handle the user actions to allow adding, removing and completing tasks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Part 2: Views</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/04/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-part-2-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/04/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-part-2-views/</guid>
      <description>In the previous article, we looked at defining our application Model using the Dojo MVC package. The model contained a list of todo tasks, each with a description and finished state, along with composite values representing the total completed and remaining task counts.
Dojo&amp;rsquo;s MVC package provides a series of widgets (Group, Output, Repeat, Generate) that assist the rendering of model attributes in our View, which automatically update when model values change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Part 1: Models</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/02/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-part-1-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/02/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-part-1-models/</guid>
      <description>In this first article, we going to look at using DojoX MVC to define our application Models, showing the use of the new StatefulModel class. Later in the series, we&amp;rsquo;ll look at binding our defined Model to a View template, rendering the HTML output and hooking into user events.
Introducing StatefulModels DojoX MVC uses a specific class for representing Models in the MVC pattern, StatefulModel. By using or extending this class, applications have access to a native JavaScript data model that integrates with all the classes under the MVC package.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Overview</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/01/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-overview/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/01/creating-todo-mvc-in-dojo-overview/</guid>
      <description>Before Christmas, Addy Osmani sent out the following tweet asking for a Dojo-version of the TodoMVC application.
Reviewing their Github page, the project aims to allow developers to compare MVC frameworks by providing implementations of a sample Todo application using different toolkit&amp;rsquo;s MVC support. They currently have over a dozen entries for toolkits, including Backbone, JavascriptMVC and Spine with more coming soon but, unfortunately, no entry for The Dojo Toolkit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>