<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>object-storage on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/object-storage/</link>
    <description>Recent content in object-storage on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/object-storage/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Hosting Static Websites on IBM Cloud</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2019/07/hosting-static-websites-on-ibm-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2019/07/hosting-static-websites-on-ibm-cloud/</guid>
      <description>This blog post explains how to host a static website on IBM Cloud. These websites are rendered client-side by the browser from static assets, like HTML, CSS and JS files. They do not need a server-side component to create pages dynamically at runtime. Static websites are often combined with backend APIs to create Single Page Applications.
Hosting static websites on IBM Cloud uses Cloud Object Storage (COS) and Cloud Internet Services (CIS) (with Page Rules and Edge Functions).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Cloud Object Storage from IBM Cloud Functions (Node.js)</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2018/05/using-cloud-object-storage-from-ibm-cloud-functions-node.js/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2018/05/using-cloud-object-storage-from-ibm-cloud-functions-node.js/</guid>
      <description>How do you manage files for a serverless application? 🤔
Previous blog posts discussed this common problem and introduced the most popular solution, using a cloud-based object storage service. 👏👏👏
Object stores provide elastic storage in the cloud, with a billing model which charges for capacity used. These services are the storage solution for serverless applications, which do not have access to a traditional file system. 👍
I&amp;rsquo;m now going to demonstrate how to use IBM Cloud Object Storage from IBM Cloud Functions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>File Storage For Serverless Applications</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2018/04/file-storage-for-serverless-applications/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2018/04/file-storage-for-serverless-applications/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Where do you store files without a server?&amp;quot;
 …is the most common question I get asked during Q&amp;amp;A after one of my &amp;ldquo;Introduction to Serverless Platforms&amp;rdquo; conference talks. Searching for this question online, this is the answer you will often find.
 &amp;ldquo;Use an object store for file storage and access using the S3-compatible interface. Provide direct access to files by making buckets public and return pre-signed URLs for uploading content.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>