<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: logs | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/logs/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2019-07-03T14:10:55+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Openwhisk Logstash Forwarder]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/11/21/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder/"/>
    <updated>2017-11-21T17:15:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/11/21/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder/master/.resources/kibana_copy.png" title="Kibana Dashboard with OpenWhisk Logs" alt="Kibana Dashboard" /></p>

<p>Debugging serverless applications in production is often reliant on application logs, due to having no access to the runtime environment. No SSHing into the machine and attaching a debugger to a process or using strace to dump system calls.</p>

<p>Storing, searching and analysing serverless application logs is crucial to diagnosing and fixing bugs on serverless platforms.</p>

<p>The "<a href="https://www.oreilly.com/ideas/understanding-the-elk-stack">ELK Stack</a>" has become a popular solution for managing applications logs. Combining three open-source projects (<a href="https://github.com/elastic/elasticsearch">ElasticSearch</a>, <a href="https://github.com/elastic/logstash">Logstash</a> and <a href="https://github.com/elastic/kibana">Kibana</a>), this solution provides a scalable platform for importing, storing and searching application logs.</p>

<p><strong><em>How can we use the ELK stack to manage logs for serverless applications running on Apache OpenWhisk?</em></strong></p>

<h3>ELK and OpenWhisk</h3>

<p>In traditional application runtimes, like a VM or a Docker container, a <a href="https://michael.bouvy.net/blog/en/2013/12/06/use-lumberjack-logstash-forwarder-to-forward-logs-logstash/">background agent</a> is used to automatically forward application and system logs to the ingestion service for the ELK stack.</p>

<p>However, serverless applications run in an <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/serverless.html">ephemeral environment</a>. Runtimes are instantiated on-demand per request and destroyed after the function returns. These runtimes do not support the use of background agents.</p>

<p>One solution for this is the <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/logstash-input-openwhisk">custom OpenWhisk plugin</a> for Logstash. This plugin polls the platform for new logs and automatically ingests them into ElasticSearch.</p>

<p><strong><em>But what if you are using a hosted ELK service that does not support installing custom plugins?</em></strong></p>

<h3>OpenWhisk Logstash Forwarder</h3>

<p>"<a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder">OpenWhisk Logstash Forwarder</a>" is designed for this scenario. It can ingest logs into ElasticSearch using standard Logstash input plugins.</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder">https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder</a></p>

<p>This project contains an <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/docs/actions.md">OpenWhisk action</a> which acts as a "serverless" version of the logstash-forwarder agent. When the action executes, it retrieves all new logs from a user-provided list of actions to monitor. Log messages are pushed into Logstash using the <a href="https://www.elastic.co/guide/en/logstash/current/plugins-inputs-lumberjack.html">Lumberjack protocol</a>.</p>

<p>The action is connected to an <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk-package-alarms">alarm trigger feed</a> with a <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk-package-alarms#firing-a-trigger-event-periodically">customisable schedule</a>. This event source will ensure all logs are forwarded on a regular schedule.</p>

<h3>Demo</h3>

<p><img src="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder/master/.resources/demo.gif" title="OpenWhisk Logs with ElasticSearch Demo" alt="Demo" /></p>

<p>In this example, the developer has the serverless logstash forwarder agent deployed in their workspace. The agent is configured to monitor logs from the <code>forecast</code> action. The alarm trigger feed is connected to the monitoring action and runs once per minute.</p>

<p>Invoking the <code>forecast</code> action generates log messages to be ingested.</p>

<p>When the alarm trigger feed next fires, the monitoring action is executed. It retrieves log messages generated by new <code>forecast</code> activations and pushes those logs into the configured ELK instance.</p>

<p>Opening Kibana and refreshing the monitoring dashboard, new log messages are shown as individual documents. Selecting the individual documents shows the log message contents with activation record details.</p>

<h3>Source Code</h3>

<p>The source code for this project is now available on Github:</p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder">https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder</a></p>

<p>See the <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk-logstash-forwarder#installation">installation instructions</a> for how to deploy this project on an OpenWhisk platform.</p>

<p>This project needs an instance of OpenWhisk platform and an ELK-stack service accessible on a public IP address.</p>

<p>This project can be deployed using <a href="https://serverless.com/">The Serverless Framework</a> or the <a href="https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk-cli">OpenWhisk CLI</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
