<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>node-red on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/node-red/</link>
    <description>Recent content in node-red on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/node-red/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>OpenWhisk and Node-RED</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2016/09/openwhisk-and-node-red/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2016/09/openwhisk-and-node-red/</guid>
      <description>Node-RED nodes for OpenWhisk were initially released earlier this year. The nodes allowed users to manually invoke existing Actions and Triggers. This month, a new version of the package has been released providing a huge improvement in the functionality…
features  Users can now define new Actions using the flow editor UI, providing the source code through the inline node configuration panel. Users can also modify existing Actions, with the live Action source being previewed in the node editor panel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Node-RED Docker Images</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2016/07/node-red-docker-images/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2016/07/node-red-docker-images/</guid>
      <description>This week, I&amp;rsquo;ve been helping create and publish official Docker images for the Node-RED project. Users can start Node-RED instances from these images using the following command.
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 nodered/node-red-docker Node-RED is now publishing the following images to Docker Hub for each new release.
 latest - uses official Node.JS v4 base image. slim - uses Alpine Linux base image. rpi - uses RPi-compatible base image.  When a new version is released on NPM, an automated CI service will build, test and publish new images with the updated version tags.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>NPM Modules in Node-RED</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2016/01/npm-modules-in-node-red/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2016/01/npm-modules-in-node-red/</guid>
      <description>Before Christmas, my department at IBM had one of our semi-regular Hack Days to get everyone together and work on interesting ideas away from the day job. I spent the time playing with an idea to make exposing NPM packages in Node-RED easier&amp;hellip;
 Node-RED is a visual tool for wiring the Internet of Things.
 It makes it easy to create, combine and control data flowing between hardware devices, web APIs and open protocols.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Updated IBM Watson Nodes for Node-RED</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2016/01/updated-ibm-watson-nodes-for-node-red/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2016/01/updated-ibm-watson-nodes-for-node-red/</guid>
      <description>Earlier this year, I made a major upate to the Node-RED nodes for the IBM Watson services available through IBM Bluemix. Since then, the IBM Watson team has been busy, with lots of changes to APIs. I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been working through these changes, updating the nodes, to ensure they work against the latest APIs.
Updates to these nodes have now been finished and are available through the boilerplate on IBM Bluemix or by installing the IBM Bluemix Nodes package locally.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AlchemyAPI &amp;amp; Updated Watson Nodes for Node-RED</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2015/07/alchemyapi-amp-updated-watson-nodes-for-node-red/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2015/07/alchemyapi-amp-updated-watson-nodes-for-node-red/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve recently been working on a number of updates to the Node-RED nodes for the IBM Bluemix platform&amp;hellip;
Highlights below:
New AlchemyAPI Nodes There are two new nodes (Feature Extract and Image Extract) in the package, allowing users to call services from the AlchemyAPI platform.
  Feature Extract. This node will analyse external URLs, HTML or text content with features for text-based analysis from the AlchemyAPI service, e.g. keywords, sentiment, relationships, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IBM Watson Nodes For Node-RED</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2015/04/ibm-watson-nodes-for-node-red/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2015/04/ibm-watson-nodes-for-node-red/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve updated the IBM Watson Nodes for Node-RED to include seven extra services.
Previously, the package only provided support for the following services:
 Language Identification. Machine Translation. Question &amp;amp; Answers.  With the recent code changes, users now have access to the additional services:
 Message Resonance. Personality Insights. Relationship Extraction. Speech to Text. Text to Speech. Tradeoff Analytics. Visual Recognition.  Using Node-RED through the IBM Bluemix boilerplate will automatically include the IBM Watson modules in the palette.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>