<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: alchemyapi | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/alchemyapi/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2019-01-18T15:22:17+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated IBM Watson Nodes for Node-RED]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/01/04/updated-ibm-watson-nodes/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T15:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/01/04/updated-ibm-watson-nodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/node-red-updates.png %}</p>

<p>Earlier this year, I made a <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2015/04/22/ibm-watson-nodes-for-nodered/">major upate</a> to the Node-RED nodes for the IBM
Watson services available through IBM Bluemix. Since then, the IBM Watson team
has been <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/watson/blog">busy</a>, with lots of changes to APIs. I've recently been working through
these changes, updating the nodes, to ensure they work against the latest APIs.</p>

<p><strong>Updates to these nodes have now been finished and are available through the
<a href="https://console.ng.bluemix.net/catalog/starters/node-red-starter/">boilerplate</a> on IBM Bluemix or by installing the <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes">IBM Bluemix Nodes</a> package
locally.</strong></p>

<p>If you have an existing Node-RED instance running in IBM Bluemix, please review
the <a href="https://www.ng.bluemix.net/docs/#starters/Node-RED/nodered.html#nodered">documentation</a> for upgrade instructions.</p>

<p>If you encounter any issues, please raise a <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/issues">issue on Github</a>.</p>

<p><em>For full details on the changes are available in the <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/pull/30">pull request</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AlchemyAPI &amp; Updated Watson Nodes for Node-RED]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2015/07/15/alchemyapi-and-updated-watson-nodes-for-node-red/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-15T16:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2015/07/15/alchemyapi-and-updated-watson-nodes-for-node-red</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/node-red-updates.png %}</p>

<p>I've recently been working on a <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/commit/56007e60d3414da3eb5c1dac766b23bdd96dd149">number</a> of <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/commit/4d0bcfe34f5e107e3b9e0684cd26ae701f913253">updates</a> to the Node-RED <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes">nodes</a> for the IBM Bluemix platform...</p>

<p>Highlights below:</p>

<h2>New AlchemyAPI Nodes</h2>

<p>There are two new nodes (Feature Extract and Image Extract) in the package, allowing users to call services from the AlchemyAPI platform.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Feature Extract.</em> This node will analyse external URLs, HTML or text content with features for text-based analysis
from the AlchemyAPI service, e.g. keywords, sentiment, relationships, etc.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Image Analysis.</em> This node will analyse images, passed in as external URLs or raw image bytes, to extract faces, content and URLs.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Configuration for each node is available through the node editor panel.</p>

<p>For full details on all the capabilities of the AlchemyAPI platform, please see their <a href="http://www.alchemyapi.com/api">documentation</a>.</p>

<h2>Updated IBM Watson Nodes</h2>

<p>With the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/watson/blog/2015/07/06/ibm-watson-language-translation-and-speech-services-general-availability/">recent changes</a>
to the IBM Watson services, there were a number of changes needed to support the API changes. All the IBM Watson nodes now work with the GA versions
of the services.</p>

<p><strong>Users must ensure they are using GA versions of the service with the nodes. Details on migration steps are available on the IBM Watson
<a href="https://developer.ibm.com/watson/blog/2015/07/06/ibm-watson-language-translation-and-speech-services-general-availability/">blog post</a> about the updates.</strong></p>

<h2>Running Locally</h2>

<p>When running Node-RED on IBM Bluemix, credentials for the services bound to the application are automatically registered. Previously, running the nodes
outside of IBM Bluemix required complex configuration to register service credentials. With this release, users will
be prompted to input the service credentials in the node editor panel if the application isn't running on IBM Bluemix. Much easier!</p>

<p><strong>If you have questions or encounter issues, please ask over on <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/node-red">Stackoverflow</a> or raise <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/issues">issues</a> in Github</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
