<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>node js on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/node-js/</link>
    <description>Recent content in node js on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/node-js/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Cloud Foundry Custom Buildpacks</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2015/03/cloud-foundry-custom-buildpacks/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Mar 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2015/03/cloud-foundry-custom-buildpacks/</guid>
      <description>Cloud Foundry Buildpacks provide runtime and framework support for applications. Users can rely on the built-in selection for Java, NodeJS, Python, etc. or additional community buildpacks from Github.
Buildpacks are open-source, making them simple to customise and include libraries needed by your application.
Doctor Watson uses an NPM module that relies on a command-line application, SOX, being installed in the runtime environment.
Making this command-line application available on the platform required the project to create a custom NodeJS buildpack.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Doctor Watson</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2015/02/doctor-watson/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2015/02/doctor-watson/</guid>
      <description>Doctor Watson is an IBM Bluemix application to answer medical questions over the phone, using IBM Watson and Twilio.
Ringing an external phone number, the application will answer and ask for a medical question to help with. Translating your speech into text and using IBM Watson&amp;rsquo;s Question and Answer service, Doctor Watson will query the medical corpus.
Top rated answers will be converted to speech and used as a response over the phone.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>