<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: microservices | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/microservices/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-04T16:17:47+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Microservices Without Servers]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/09/08/microservices-without-servers/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-08T16:17:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/09/08/microservices-without-servers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>…is the title of my presentation about building serverless applications using OpenWhisk.</p>

<script async class="speakerdeck-embed" data-id="387717983473473bb9eed49d50e6e279" data-ratio="1.77777777777778" src="http://jamesthom.as//speakerdeck.com/assets/embed.js"></script>


<h2>Abstract</h2>

<p><em>Servers are killing your productivity. Rather than building better software for your users, you end up constantly distracted by maintaining computers. Wasn't the "cloud" supposed to fix this? It sounded so promising until we realised it was just renting VMs in someone else's datacenter. We couldn't escape "servers". Until now...</em></p>

<p><em>In this session, developers will learn how to build microservices without servers, using modern “serverless” cloud platforms. We’ll look at common challenges (and solutions) to building applications using “serverless” stacks. Exploring emerging “serverless” design patterns will give developers the knowledge to build application architectures using these new platforms.</em></p>

<p><em>This session is aimed at software developers experienced in building traditional backend web applications, who want to learn how to build microservices without servers.</em></p>

<h2>Slides, Code, Videos</h2>

<p>Slides for the talk are available <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/jthomas/microservices-without-servers">here</a>.</p>

<p>There's a Github repository with resources <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/microservices_without_servers">from the talk</a>, including a <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/microservices_without_servers/blob/master/transcript.md">transcript</a>, <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/microservices_without_servers/blob/master/code">code demos</a> and <a href="https://www.youtube.com/playlist?list=PL0UyhC0D6KABYPvGroXcIeE-4x_yEbdB4">videos</a>.</p>

<p>If you have questions or issues, raise an issue in the repository or send me a <a href="https://twitter.com/thomasj">tweet</a>.</p>

<h2>Conference Sessions</h2>

<p>This talk was <a href="http://www.jday.com.ua/#nav-schedule">first delivered</a> at <a href="https://http://www.jday.com.ua/">JDayLviv</a> earlier this month. The session was recorded so the video should surface online soon. I'll be repeating the talk at <a href="https://belgrade.voxxeddays.com/talk/145/">VoxxedDays Belgrade</a> and <a href="http://javaday.org.ua/kyiv/#speakers">JavaDay Kiev</a> in September and October.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
