<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>presentations on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/presentations/</link>
    <description>Recent content in presentations on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/presentations/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>London JS - Watson</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/10/london-js-watson/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/10/london-js-watson/</guid>
      <description>Last month, I was invited to speak at LondonJS on the machine learning and artificial intelligence behind IBM Watson.
I jokingly said the talk would win the prize for the &amp;ldquo;least amount of JavaScript-related content in a LondonJS talk&amp;rdquo;.
The idea was to introduce the audience to topics (machine learning) that might be relevant in the future and IBM Watson was a great example that people love hearing about.
Slides for the event are now posted online, check them out here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IBM IMPACT 2012 - Session Materials Available</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/05/ibm-impact-2012-session-materials-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/05/ibm-impact-2012-session-materials-available/</guid>
      <description>Last week was IBM IMPACT 2012, IBM&amp;rsquo;s premier conference for our customers in Las Vegas. I was fortunate enough to be there for the duration, presentating four sessions on The Dojo Toolkit. The whole event was a fantastic showcase for our company, the capabilities and unique values we provide. Session materials from my talks are now available externally, see below for individual links.
IBM IMPACT Sessions  Optimizing Your Dojo Application Using The Dojo Build System Moving to Dojo 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming Talks</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/04/upcoming-talks/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/04/upcoming-talks/</guid>
      <description>Next month I&amp;rsquo;ll be presenting at IBM IMPACT 2012, IBM&amp;rsquo;s premier customer conference in Las Vegas from April 29th until May 4th. I&amp;rsquo;ve had three sessions accepted, full details below. If you&amp;rsquo;re attending the conference and want to say hello, please let me know.
This week I was invited to present a preview of the joint session I&amp;rsquo;m doing with Dylan Schiemann at IMPACT for London AJAX. There was a really great crowd of over seventy developers waiting to hear all about AMD.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>