<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>conference on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/conference/</link>
    <description>Recent content in conference on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/conference/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Monki Gras</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2013/02/monki-gras/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2013/02/monki-gras/</guid>
      <description>Last week was Monki Gras, the conference organised by RedMonk, with this year&amp;rsquo;s theme being &amp;ldquo;scaling craft&amp;rdquo;.
 We plan to explore Craft that helps scale Technology, or Technology that helps scale Craft. What are the limits of a craft-based approach? Does quality have to suffer as businesses scale? James Governor http://redmonk.com/jgovernor/2013/01/07/scaling-craft-tech-and-beer-monki-gras-conference-2013/
 Held over two days in London&amp;rsquo;s Conway Hall, there was an incredible line-up of speakers, social events and evening activities.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IBM IMPACT 2012 - Session Materials Available</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2012/05/ibm-impact-2012-session-materials-available/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2012/05/ibm-impact-2012-session-materials-available/</guid>
      <description>Last week was IBM IMPACT 2012, IBM&amp;rsquo;s premier conference for our customers in Las Vegas. I was fortunate enough to be there for the duration, presentating four sessions on The Dojo Toolkit. The whole event was a fantastic showcase for our company, the capabilities and unique values we provide. Session materials from my talks are now available externally, see below for individual links.
IBM IMPACT Sessions  Optimizing Your Dojo Application Using The Dojo Build System Moving to Dojo 1.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>DojoConf 2011 - Building Dojo In The Cloud</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2011/10/dojoconf-2011-building-dojo-in-the-cloud/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Oct 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2011/10/dojoconf-2011-building-dojo-in-the-cloud/</guid>
      <description>September saw this year&amp;rsquo;s Dojo Conference hit Washington, D.C for two days. Attending as one of this year&amp;rsquo;s speakers, I was given the second slot on Saturday morning to talk about the Dojo Web Builder. The presentation covered why we built the tool, what it can do (including a live demo), a high-level overview of the architecture and finished looking at how users have been using the tool since it launched in April.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>