<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: node-red | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/node-red/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-04T15:51:39+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[OpenWhisk and Node-RED]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/09/26/node-red-and-openwhisk/"/>
    <updated>2016-09-26T15:16:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/09/26/node-red-and-openwhisk</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/node-red-node-openwhisk">Node-RED nodes for OpenWhisk</a> were initially released earlier this year. The nodes allowed users to manually invoke existing Actions and Triggers. This month, a <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-node-openwhisk/releases/tag/0.3.0">new version of the package</a> has been released providing a huge improvement in the functionality…</p>

<h3>features</h3>

<ul>
<li>Users can now define new Actions using the flow editor UI, providing the source code through the inline node configuration panel.</li>
<li>Users can also modify existing Actions, with the live Action source being previewed in the node editor panel.</li>
<li>Triggers can be created and updated in the same way.</li>
<li>Both nodes allow users to view, define and modify default parameters for both Actions and Triggers.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Deploying the flow will make the modifications to Actions and Triggers live for the configured OpenWhisk platform.</em></p>

<h3>example</h3>

<p>This video shows the updated nodes being used to define a new OpenWhisk Action, invoking it in response to a message from an inject node and then making modifications to the source code.</p>

<p>{% img /images/NR_and_OW.gif %}</p>

<h3>interested?</h3>

<p>Grab the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/node-red-node-openwhisk">updated NPM package</a> to test the new features out today…</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Node-RED Docker Images]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/07/27/node-red-docker-images/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-27T15:24:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/07/27/node-red-docker-images</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This week, I've been helping create and publish official <a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> images for the
<a href="http://nodered.org/">Node-RED</a> project. Users can start Node-RED instances from these images using the following command.</p>

<p><code>
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 nodered/node-red-docker
</code></p>

<p>Node-RED is now publishing the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/nodered/node-red-docker/">following images to Docker Hub</a> for each new release.</p>

<ul>
<li><strong><a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-docker/tree/master/latest">latest</a></strong> - uses <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/node/">official Node.JS v4 base image</a>.</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-docker/tree/master/slim">slim</a></strong> - uses <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/mhart/alpine-node/">Alpine Linux base image</a>.</li>
<li><strong><a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-docker/tree/master/rpi">rpi</a></strong> - uses <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/hypriot/rpi-node/">RPi-compatible base image</a>.</li>
</ul>


<p>When a new version is <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/node-red">released on NPM</a>, an <a href="https://travis-ci.org/node-red/node-red-docker">automated CI service</a> will build, test and
publish new images with the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/nodered/node-red-docker/tags/">updated version tags</a>.</p>

<p>The source repository for the Docker images is available at <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-docker">https://github.com/node-red/node-red-docker</a>.</p>

<h2>Background</h2>

<p>There was a <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red/issues/603">long-standing issue</a> open with the project
to provide official Docker images for the tool. Many users had <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/cpswan/node-red/">already</a> <a href="https://github.com/jamesbrink/docker-node-red">been</a>
<a href="http://ivyco.blogspot.co.uk/2015/03/docker-awesomeness.html">experimenting</a> with Node-RED and Docker.</p>

<p><em>Reviewing the community's efforts, we wanted to create official images that
made it simple for users to start Node-RED as Docker containers with minimal
configuration whilst allowing for easy customisation, i.e. adding new nodes.</em></p>

<p>Docker images are created using a configuration file (<a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/">Dockerfile</a>) that lists the
commands to build that image and can start by <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/#/from">using another image as the 'base'</a>.</p>

<p>Node-RED is a Node.js application, published as an <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/node-red">NPM module</a>.
The Node.js project publishes <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/node/">official Docker images</a> which we used as our base image.
These images provide an environment with the correct versions of Node.js and
NPM installed.</p>

<p>Rather than manually copying the Node-RED source code into the container image,
we used NPM to install the source code by defining a custom <a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/files/package.json">package.json</a>
which includes Node-RED as dependency.</p>

<p>``` json package.json
{</p>

<pre><code>"name": "node-red-docker",
"version": "0.14.5",
"description": "Docker images for Node-RED",
"main": "node_modules/node-red/red/red.js",
"scripts": {
    "start": "node-red"
},
...
"dependencies": {
    "node-red": "0.14.5"
},
"engines": {
    "node": "4.*.*"
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Adding this file into the container image and then running <a href="https://docs.npmjs.com/cli/install">NPM install</a>, using
the <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/#/add">ADD</a> and <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/#/run">RUN</a> commands, will retrieve the correct Node-RED version and build
that into the container image.</p>

<p>Docker images define a <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/reference/builder/#/cmd">default start command</a> to run when the container is
created. Using <em>npm start</em> for this image will parse the start script
listed in the package.json file, which has been set to
<em>node-red</em>.</p>

<h2>Adding New Nodes</h2>

<p>Node-RED has a <a href="http://flows.nodered.org/">huge community</a> which produces custom nodes for everything from
accessing data from a <a href="http://flows.nodered.org/node/node-red-contrib-gpio">Raspberry Pi's sensors</a> to a <a href="http://flows.nodered.org/node/node-red-contrib-teslams">Tesla car</a>.</p>

<p>Additional nodes <a href="http://nodered.org/docs/getting-started/adding-nodes">can be installed</a> by putting the files into your user
directory, which defaults to <em>$HOME/.node-red</em>.</p>

<p>Allowing users to install additional nodes without building new images is
possible using <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/tutorials/dockervolumes/">Docker's volume support</a>. Docker data volumes can be used to
share files between the container and the host system, by <a href="https://docs.docker.com/engine/tutorials/dockervolumes/#/mount-a-host-directory-as-a-data-volume">mounting a directory on the host as a data volume within the container</a>.</p>

<p>Exposing the Node-RED user directory within the container as a data volume
means users can mount this on the host system. Nodes installed into this
directory, using NPM on the host system, will automatically be registered when
Node-RED starts.</p>

<p>Within the Dockerfile for the Node-RED image, the /data directory is configured
as the user directory and <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-docker/blob/master/latest/Dockerfile#L23">exported as a data volume</a>.</p>

<p>Users can mount their local user directory into the container with the
following command.</p>

<p><code>sh
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 -v ~/.node-red:/data nodered/node-red-docker
</code></p>

<h2>Environment Parameters</h2>

<p>Docker <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/30494050/how-to-pass-environment-variables-to-docker-containers">supports injecting environment parameter</a> values into running containers,
using command-line options on the host system. This is often used to configure
runtime options without users having to build new container images. Node-RED's
Docker images support the following environment parameters.</p>

<h3>Flows Configuration</h3>

<p>User flow configurations are <a href="http://nodered.org/docs/getting-started/running">stored in a JSON file under the user directory</a>. This defaults to
<em>flows.json</em> but can be configured using an environment parameter
(<strong>FLOWS</strong>) passed to the container, as shown below.</p>

<p><code>
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 -e FLOWS=my_flows.json nodered/node-red-docker
</code></p>

<h3>Node Options</h3>

<p>Node.js runtime arguments can be passed to the container using an environment
parameter (<strong>NODE_OPTIONS</strong>). For example, to <a href="https://github.com/nodejs/node/issues/2738">fix the heap size</a> used by the Node.js
garbage collector you would use the following command.</p>

<p><code>
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 -e NODE_OPTIONS="--max_old_space_size=128" nodered/node-red-docker
</code></p>

<h2>Alpine Linux Image</h2>

<p>The official Node.js Docker image uses the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/debian/">Debian Jessie base image</a>. This image
provides a full Linux install, which means dependent Docker images can be
hundreds of megabytes in size. Node-RED's Docker image, using this base image,
is nearly 300 MB.</p>

<p>Reducing Docker image sizes can <a href="http://jasonwilder.com/blog/2014/08/19/squashing-docker-images/">dramatically reduce build and deployment times</a>.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.alpinelinux.org/">Alpine Linux</a> is a lightweight Linux distribution, focused on security and
performance. A <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/alpine/">minimal Docker image</a> based on Alpine Linux is only 5 MB in
size!</p>

<p>Using the <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/mhart/alpine-node/">alpine-node</a> base
image, which provides an Alpine Linux environment with Node.js &amp; NPM, in our
Dockerfiles reduces the resulting image file to under 50 MB.</p>

<p>Alpine Linux does make it <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/36202095/node-serialport-failing-on-alpine-linux">more difficult to install NPM modules with native dependencies</a>, due to missing common libraries and tools needed to build them.</p>

<p>Therefore, we're publishing the Alpine Linux image as a seperate tag (<em>slim</em>), rather
than using this base image throughout our Dockerfiles.</p>

<p>This version should provide an extremely lightweight Node-RED image that works
for most users.</p>

<p><code>
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 nodered/node-red-docker:slim
</code></p>

<h2>Raspberry Pi Image</h2>

<p>Node-RED is an incredibly popular tool for hacking on the <a href="https://www.raspberrypi.org/">Raspberry Pi</a>. Using a
<a href="http://blog.hypriot.com/getting-started-with-docker-on-your-arm-device/">custom Raspberry Pi image</a>, developers can also have a full Docker system
running in the Linux environment on their device.</p>

<p><strong>So, can we use Docker to start Node-RED on the Raspberry Pi?</strong></p>

<p>Due to the platform architecture, ARM rather than x86/x64 by Intel or AMD,
Docker images must be packaged specifically for that platform. The existing
Docker images created for Node-RED will not work.</p>

<p>Fortunately, there's an <a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/hypriot/rpi-node/">existing RPi-compatible Docker image</a>
with Node.js and NPM.</p>

<p>Using this base image to build a new Raspberry Pi-specific Node-RED image,
published with the <em>rpi</em> tag, means users can now start Node-RED on the Raspberry Pi using Docker.</p>

<p><code>
docker run -it -p 1880:1880 nodered/node-red-docker:rpi
</code></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Updated IBM Watson Nodes for Node-RED]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/01/04/updated-ibm-watson-nodes/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T15:45:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/01/04/updated-ibm-watson-nodes</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/node-red-updates.png %}</p>

<p>Earlier this year, I made a <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2015/04/22/ibm-watson-nodes-for-nodered/">major upate</a> to the Node-RED nodes for the IBM
Watson services available through IBM Bluemix. Since then, the IBM Watson team
has been <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/watson/blog">busy</a>, with lots of changes to APIs. I've recently been working through
these changes, updating the nodes, to ensure they work against the latest APIs.</p>

<p><strong>Updates to these nodes have now been finished and are available through the
<a href="https://console.ng.bluemix.net/catalog/starters/node-red-starter/">boilerplate</a> on IBM Bluemix or by installing the <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes">IBM Bluemix Nodes</a> package
locally.</strong></p>

<p>If you have an existing Node-RED instance running in IBM Bluemix, please review
the <a href="https://www.ng.bluemix.net/docs/#starters/Node-RED/nodered.html#nodered">documentation</a> for upgrade instructions.</p>

<p>If you encounter any issues, please raise a <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/issues">issue on Github</a>.</p>

<p><em>For full details on the changes are available in the <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/pull/30">pull request</a>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[NPM Modules in Node-RED]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/01/04/npm-modules-in-node-red/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-04T15:40:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/01/04/npm-modules-in-node-red</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before Christmas, <a href="https://www-304.ibm.com/connections/blogs/et/entry/home?lang=en_us">my department</a>
at IBM had one of our semi-regular Hack Days to
get everyone together and work on interesting ideas away from the day job. I spent
the time playing with an idea to make exposing NPM packages in <a href="http://nodered.org">Node-RED</a> easier...</p>

<p>{% blockquote %}
Node-RED is a visual tool for wiring the Internet of Things.
{% endblockquote %}</p>

<p>It makes it easy to create, combine and control data flowing between hardware
devices, web APIs and open protocols. The tool exposes operations through a
series of <em>nodes</em>, which can be created through the browser-based editor and
connected to other nodes to create <em>message flows</em>.</p>

<p>The tool comes built-in with a <a href="http://flows.nodered.org/">huge selection of nodes</a>, from connecting to a
Raspberry Pi to handling HTTP requests, for creating flows. Users <a href="http://nodered.org/docs/creating-nodes/">create their own nodes</a>
to expose new functionality, by creating small modules using JavaScript and HTML.
People often wrap existing <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">NPM modules</a> into custom Node-RED nodes to use that module functionality in flows.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.npmjs.com/">NPM</a> has over two hundred thousand modules, many of which provide simple
"stateless" functions that return a result based upon the input data. These
modules are ideally suited for using within Node-RED message flows.</p>

<p>Exposing multiple new NPM modules required creating custom Node-RED nodes for every
module you wanted to use. Whilst the Node-RED node boilerplate is small,
it becomes a bit laborious and repetitive to keep doing this for extremely simple modules.</p>

<p>Wondering how to make this easier, I started hacking on ideas.</p>

<h2><em>Two days later...</em></h2>

<p>{% blockquote node-red-contrib-npm http://flows.nodered.org/node/node-red-contrib-npm %}
Node-RED node to dynamically expose NPM modules as nodes.
{% endblockquote %}</p>

<p>{% img /images/npm-start.png %}</p>

<p>This new node allows you to dynamically expose NPM modules as Node-RED nodes
without needing to manually create new nodes for them.</p>

<p>Using the node editor panel, the user can set the name of the NPM package to
expose along with the module invocation style.</p>

<p>{% img /images/npm-configure.png %}</p>

<p>Incoming flow messages are
passed as an argument to the function being executed. Users can set up the node
to call the module, a module function or even run custom setup code in response
to incoming messages.</p>

<p>Execution results, either returned directly or asynchronously
(Promises and callback-style supported), are sent as the outgoing message
payload.</p>

<p>When the flow is deployed, the NPM module will be automatically installed and instantiated.</p>

<p>Now we don't have to write lots of extra boilerplate code every time we
want to use a tiny NPM module in a Node-RED flow, hurrah!</p>

<p><em>Here's a short demonstration using the node to expose the <a href="https://www.npmjs.com/package/sentiment">sentiment</a> package
in a flow:</em></p>

<p>{% img /images/Node-RED-NPM.gif %}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[AlchemyAPI &amp; Updated Watson Nodes for Node-RED]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2015/07/15/alchemyapi-and-updated-watson-nodes-for-node-red/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-15T16:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2015/07/15/alchemyapi-and-updated-watson-nodes-for-node-red</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>{% img /images/node-red-updates.png %}</p>

<p>I've recently been working on a <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/commit/56007e60d3414da3eb5c1dac766b23bdd96dd149">number</a> of <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/commit/4d0bcfe34f5e107e3b9e0684cd26ae701f913253">updates</a> to the Node-RED <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes">nodes</a> for the IBM Bluemix platform...</p>

<p>Highlights below:</p>

<h2>New AlchemyAPI Nodes</h2>

<p>There are two new nodes (Feature Extract and Image Extract) in the package, allowing users to call services from the AlchemyAPI platform.</p>

<ul>
<li><p><em>Feature Extract.</em> This node will analyse external URLs, HTML or text content with features for text-based analysis
from the AlchemyAPI service, e.g. keywords, sentiment, relationships, etc.</p></li>
<li><p><em>Image Analysis.</em> This node will analyse images, passed in as external URLs or raw image bytes, to extract faces, content and URLs.</p></li>
</ul>


<p>Configuration for each node is available through the node editor panel.</p>

<p>For full details on all the capabilities of the AlchemyAPI platform, please see their <a href="http://www.alchemyapi.com/api">documentation</a>.</p>

<h2>Updated IBM Watson Nodes</h2>

<p>With the <a href="https://developer.ibm.com/watson/blog/2015/07/06/ibm-watson-language-translation-and-speech-services-general-availability/">recent changes</a>
to the IBM Watson services, there were a number of changes needed to support the API changes. All the IBM Watson nodes now work with the GA versions
of the services.</p>

<p><strong>Users must ensure they are using GA versions of the service with the nodes. Details on migration steps are available on the IBM Watson
<a href="https://developer.ibm.com/watson/blog/2015/07/06/ibm-watson-language-translation-and-speech-services-general-availability/">blog post</a> about the updates.</strong></p>

<h2>Running Locally</h2>

<p>When running Node-RED on IBM Bluemix, credentials for the services bound to the application are automatically registered. Previously, running the nodes
outside of IBM Bluemix required complex configuration to register service credentials. With this release, users will
be prompted to input the service credentials in the node editor panel if the application isn't running on IBM Bluemix. Much easier!</p>

<p><strong>If you have questions or encounter issues, please ask over on <a href="http://stackoverflow.com/questions/tagged/node-red">Stackoverflow</a> or raise <a href="https://github.com/node-red/node-red-bluemix-nodes/issues">issues</a> in Github</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
