<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: ibm | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/ibm/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-31T11:55:04+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Zero Downtime Deployments Using IBM Bluemix]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2014/07/22/zero-downtime-deployments-using-bluemix/"/>
    <updated>2014-07-22T14:42:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2014/07/22/zero-downtime-deployments-using-bluemix</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here's a video I've made showing you how to deploy new versions of an
application on IBM Bluemix without the end-user having to suffer any down time:</p>

<iframe width="420" height="315" src="http://jamesthom.as//www.youtube.com/embed/yfLi2hLfgSU" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p>Utilising the <a href="http://martinfowler.com/bliki/BlueGreenDeployment.html">Blue Green deployment pattern</a>, we deploy the
new version to a separate host within the production environment, rather than
taking down and updating the existing application. The HTTP router in front of
the applications controls tunnelling application requests between the different
versions. Once we verified the new version is working correctly, we can turn
off the previous version and transfer all traffic to the new instance.</p>

<p><strong>This complex deployment pattern is automatically supported by the Cloud Foundry
technology underpinning IBM Bluemix</strong>.</p>

<p><em>Staging multiple versions of an application, bound to the same external address, with automatic load balancing is handled transparently by the platform.</em></p>

<p><em>This works for any language or
runtime without any modifications to your application.</em></p>

<p>There are a few <a href="https://www.ng.%20bluemix.net/docs/#manageapps/index-gentopic3.html#d2e1">different ways</a>
to achieve this deployment approach using the
platform. The example in the video only uses three commands
with the ‘cf’ tool.</p>

<p>```sh
// Rename the existing application to allow staging a new instance without
// overwriting existing version.<br/>
$ cf rename app old_app</p>

<p>// Deploy the updated application, which will be bound to the same external
// address. HTTP traffic is load balanced between the two versions automatically.
$ cf push</p>

<p>// Verify the new application is working and then turn off the old instance.
$ cf stop old_app
```
<strong>Amazing!</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
