<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>python on notes on software.</title>
    <link>https://jamesthom.as/tags/python/</link>
    <description>Recent content in python on notes on software.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://jamesthom.as/tags/python/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Serverless APIs for MAX models</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2019/07/serverless-apis-for-max-models/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2019/07/serverless-apis-for-max-models/</guid>
      <description>IBM&amp;rsquo;s Model Asset eXchange provides a curated list of free Machine Learning models for developers. Models currently published include detecting emotions or ages in faces from images, forecasting the weather, converting speech to text and more. Models are pre-trained and ready for use in the cloud.
Models are published as series of public Docker images. Images automatically expose a HTTP API for model predictions. Documentation in the model repositories explains how to run images locally (using Docker) or deploy to the cloud (using Kubernetes).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large Applications on OpenWhisk</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2017/08/large-applications-on-openwhisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2017/08/large-applications-on-openwhisk/</guid>
      <description>OpenWhisk supports creating actions from archive files containing source files and project dependencies.
 The maximum code size for the action is 48MB. OpenWhisk system details, https://github.com/apache/incubator-openwhisk/blob/master/docs/reference.md#per-action-artifact-mb-fixed-48mb
 Applications with lots of third-party modules, native libraries or external tools may be soon find themselves running into this limit. Node.js libraries are notorious for having large amounts of dependencies.
What if you need to deploy an application larger than this limit to OpenWhisk?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Python Packages in OpenWhisk</title>
      <link>https://jamesthom.as/2017/04/python-packages-in-openwhisk/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 27 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jamesthom.as/2017/04/python-packages-in-openwhisk/</guid>
      <description>OpenWhisk&amp;rsquo;s Python runtime includes popular third-party libraries like requests, scrapy and simplejson. Developers don&amp;rsquo;t have to manually install packages to use those libraries.
Great, but what about using other libraries that aren&amp;rsquo;t pre-installed?
In a previous blog post, we showed how to deploy Node.js actions from zip files containing third-party modules. These modules are then made available in the Node.js runtime.
Recent updates to OpenWhisk allow us to use the same approach with the Python runtime!</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>