<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: go | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/go/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-04T15:53:32+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Openwhisk and Go]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/01/17/openwhisk-and-go/"/>
    <updated>2017-01-17T09:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/01/17/openwhisk-and-go</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/06/21/serverless-go-actions/">In an earlier blog post</a>, I explained how to use Go language binaries on OpenWhisk using Docker-based Actions. It relied on building Docker images for each serverless function and hosting them on Docker Hub.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.ibm.com/blogs/bluemix/2017/01/docker-bluemix-openwhisk/">Recent updates</a>  to Docker-based Actions have made this process much simpler. Developers don't need to build and expose public images anymore.</p>

<p>Let's re-visit the example from the previous post and see how to get it running using this new approach…</p>

<p><strong><em>Have you seen <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/01/16/openwhisk-docker-actions/">this post</a> explaining how Docker-based Actions work? This post assumes you have already read that first.</em></strong></p>

<h2>Go Language Actions</h2>

<p>Go's <a href="https://golang.org/pkg/go/build/">build system</a> combines application source code and dependencies into a single execution binary. Bundling this binary into a zip file allows us to overwrite the <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/core/actionProxy/stub.sh">runtime stub</a> prior to invocation.</p>

<p>Runtime binaries will be executed by the <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/core/actionProxy/actionproxy.py">Python-based invoker</a> for each invocation. Request parameters will be passed as a JSON string using the first command-line argument. The invoker expects the Action result to be written to standard output as a JSON string.</p>

<h3>Action Source Code</h3>

<p>Here's a simple Go function that returns a greeting string from an input parameter. It parses the JSON string provided on the command-line to look for a <code>name</code> parameter. If this isn't present, it defaults to <code>Stranger</code>. It returns a JSON object with the greeting string (<code>msg</code>) by writing to the console.</p>

<p>``` go
package main</p>

<p>import "encoding/json"
import "fmt"
import "os"</p>

<p>func main() {</p>

<pre><code>// native actions receive one argument, the JSON object as a string
arg := os.Args[1]

// unmarshal the string to a JSON object
var obj map[string]interface{}
json.Unmarshal([]byte(arg), &amp;obj)
name, ok := obj["name"].(string)
if !ok {
    name = "Stranger"
}
msg := map[string]string{"msg": ("Hello, " + name + "!")}
res, _ := json.Marshal(msg)
fmt.Println(string(res))
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Building this locally allows us to test it works.</p>

<p><code>go
$ go run test.go '{"name": "James"}'
{"msg":"Hello, James!"}
</code></p>

<p><em>Before we can deploy this binary to OpenWhisk, it must be compiled for the platform architecture.</em></p>

<h3>Cross-Compiling Locally</h3>

<p>Go 1.5 <a href="https://dave.cheney.net/2015/08/22/cross-compilation-with-go-1-5">introduced much improved</a> support for cross-compilation.</p>

<p>If you have the development environment installed locally, you can compile the binary for another platform by setting environment variables. The full list of supported architectures is available <a href="https://golang.org/doc/install/source#environment">here</a>.</p>

<p><em>OpenWhisk uses an <a href="https://hub.docker.com/_/alpine/">Alpine Linux-based</a> environment to execute Actions.</em></p>

<p><code>sh
$ env GOOS=linux GOARCH=amd64 go build exec.go
</code></p>

<p>Checking the file type demonstrates we have built a static binary for the Linux x86_64 platform.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ file exec
exec: ELF 64-bit LSB executable, x86-64, version 1 (SYSV), statically linked, not stripped
</code></p>

<h3>Cross-Compiling Using Docker</h3>

<p>If you don't want to install the Go development toolchain, Docker can be used to start a container with the environment set up.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ docker pull golang
$ docker run -it -v $(pwd):/go/src golang
root@0a2f1655eece:/go# cd src/
root@0a2f1655eece:/go/src# go build exec.go
root@0a2f1655eece:/go/src# ls
exec  exec.go
$ file exec
exec: ELF 64-bit LSB executable, x86-64, version 1 (SYSV), statically linked, not stripped
</code></p>

<h3>Create &amp; Deploy Archive</h3>

<p>Add the binary to a zip file, ensuring the file is named <code>exec</code> in the archive.</p>

<p>Use the <code>wsk</code> command-line to create a new Docker Action using this archive.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ zip action.zip exec
  adding: exec (deflated 66%)
$ wsk action create go_test action.zip --docker
ok: created action go_test
</code></p>

<h3>Invoking Action</h3>

<p>Test the action from the command-line to verify it works.</p>

<p>```sh
$ wsk action invoke go_test --blocking --result
{</p>

<pre><code>"msg": "Hello, Stranger!"
</code></pre>

<p>}
$ wsk action invoke go_test --blocking --result --param name James
{</p>

<pre><code>"msg": "Hello, James!"
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Success 😎.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Serverless Go Actions]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/06/21/serverless-go-actions/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-21T17:01:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2016/06/21/serverless-go-actions</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>There's now a better way to do this! See here: <a href="/blog/2017/01/17/openwhisk-and-go/">http://jamesthom.as/blog/2017/01/17/openwhisk-and-go/</a></strong></p>

<p><a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk">OpenWhisk</a>, the open-source serverless
platform, provides the ability to invoke custom
<a href="https://www.docker.com/">Docker</a> containers as serverless functions.</p>

<p>Developers can create new
<a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/blob/master/docs/actions.md">Actions</a>,
referencing public images on <a href="https://dockerhub.com">Dockerhub</a>. OpenWhisk
manages creating and executing containers using these images per invocation
request.</p>

<p>Using this feature, developers can write serverless functions using the
<a href="https://golang.org/">Go language</a>. Compiled Go language binaries are embedded
within custom Docker images and pushed into the platform.</p>

<p><strong>So, how do we start?</strong></p>

<p><em>This blog post will explain how to get your Go language functions running as
"serverless functions" on OpenWhisk. If you're impatient to get to the code,
this <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_go_action">repository</a> contains the
examples for everything discussed below.</em></p>

<p>OpenWhisk helps developers create custom Actions using Docker through an SDK...</p>

<h2>OpenWhisk Docker SDK</h2>

<p>Using the
<a href="https://new-console.ng.bluemix.net/docs/openwhisk/index.html"><em>wsk</em> command-line utility</a>,
developers can install the
<a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/tree/master/sdk/docker">SDK</a> into the
current directory.</p>

<p><code>
$ wsk sdk install docker
</code></p>

<p>The SDK provides the <a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/tree/master/sdk/docker">source for a custom Docker image</a>, which executes a custom
binary in response to invocation requests. The default SDK copies the
executable file, located at the <em>client/action</em>, into the image during the
build process. Users build the image locally before pushing this to Dockerhub.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ docker build -t &lt;dockerhub_user&gt;/docker_action .
$ docker push &lt;dockerhub_user&gt;/docker_action
</code></p>

<p>Using the command-line utility, users can then create a new Action referencing
this public Docker image. When this Action is invoked, the platform will spin
up a new container from this custom image.</p>

<p><code>sh
$ wsk action create docker_action --docker &lt;dockerhub_user&gt;/docker_action
$ wsk action invoke --blocking --result docker_action
</code></p>

<h2>OpenWhisk Docker Action </h2>

<p>OpenWhisk SDK's Docker image uses a Node.js
<a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/tree/master/sdk/docker/server">application</a>
to handle the JSON invocation request from the platform and spawns a process to
execute the binary. Invocation parameters are passed as a JSON string through a
command-line argument to the binary. The executable must write the JSON
response to stdout, the handler will return this to the platform.</p>

<p>Containers used to run OpenWhisk Actions must be expose a HTTP API on port 8080
with two paths, <em>/init</em> and <em>/run</em>. The platform sends HTTP POST requests to
these paths to initialise the Action and schedule invocations.</p>

<p>The <em>/init</em> path is used to provide the Action source for languages which
support runtime evaluation. <strong>User-provided Docker images do not need to
implement this method, other than returning a non-error HTTP response.</strong></p>

<p>The <em>/run</em> path is called by the platform for each invocation request.
Parameters for the invocation are passed as the <em>value</em> property of the JSON
request body. Any non-empty JSON response will be interpreted as the invocation
result.</p>

<h2>Go Actions using the Docker SDK</h2>

<p>Using Go binaries with the Docker SDK requires the developer to cross-compile
the source for the platform architecture and copy the binary to the
<em>client/action</em> path.</p>

<p><code>
export GOARCH=386
export GOOS=linux
go build -o action
mv action client/action
</code></p>

<p>The Go code must parse the invocation parameters as a JSON string from the
command-line argument. Data written to <em>stdout</em> will be parsed as JSON and
returned as the Action response.</p>

<p>This sample Go source demonstrates using this method to implement a "reverse
string" Action.</p>

<p>``` go
package main</p>

<p>import "os"
import "encoding/json"
import "log"</p>

<p>type Params struct {
  Payload string <code>json:"payload"</code>
}</p>

<p>type Result struct {
  Reversed string <code>json:"reversed"</code>
}</p>

<p>// extract invocation parameters, passed as JSON string argument on command-line.
func params() Params {
  var params Params
  source := os.Args[1]
  buf := []byte(source)
  if err := json.Unmarshal(buf, &amp;params); err != nil {</p>

<pre><code>log.Fatal(err)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  return params
}</p>

<p>// convert struct back to JSON for response
func return_result(result Result) {
  buf, err := json.Marshal(result)
  if err != nil {</p>

<pre><code>log.Fatal(err)
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  os.Stdout.Write(buf)
}</p>

<p>func main() {
  input := params()</p>

<p>  // reverse the string passed from invocation parameters
  chars := []rune(input.Payload)
  for i, j := 0, len(chars)-1; i &lt; j; i, j = i+1, j-1 {</p>

<pre><code>chars[i], chars[j] = chars[j], chars[i]
</code></pre>

<p>  }
  result := Result{</p>

<pre><code>Reversed: string(chars),
</code></pre>

<p>  }</p>

<p>  return_result(result)
}
```</p>

<h2>Docker SDK Base Image</h2>

<p>Building a base image from the OpenWhisk Docker SDK and publishing on Dockerhub
simplifies the process of building a Docker-based Action. Developers can now
use the following image
(<a href="https://hub.docker.com/r/jamesthomas/openwhisk_docker_action/">jamesthomas/openwhisk_docker_action</a>),
without having to install the SDK locally.</p>

<p><code>
FROM jamesthomas/openwhisk_docker_action
COPY action /blackbox/action
</code></p>

<p>This base image includes the Node.js handler to manage the platform HTTP
requests. An executable file at <em>/blackbox/action</em> will be called for each
invocation. JSON parameters and responses are still passed using command-line
arguments and stdout.</p>

<h2>Custom Go Handler </h2>

<p>Using the Docker SDK for OpenWhisk relies on a Node.js application to handle
the platform HTTP requests, spawning a process to execute the user binary file.</p>

<p>Implementing the HTTP API, described above, in Go would allow us to remove the
Node.js handler from the image. Compiling the Go Action source with the HTTP
API handler into a single binary and using an Alpine Linux base image will
dramatically reduce the image size.</p>

<p>This should improve execution performance, by removing the Node.js VM process,
and cold start-up time, through having a smaller Docker image.</p>

<p><strong>Using this Go package, <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/ow">jthomas/ow</a>, users can
automate the process of creating Go-based Actions.</strong></p>

<p><code>
go get jthomas/ow
</code></p>

<p><em>The package provides a method for registering Action callbacks and implements
the HTTP endpoints for handling platform requests.</em></p>

<p><em>Invocation parameters are passed using a function parameter, rather than a raw
JSON string. Returned interface values will be automatically serialised to JSON
as the Action response.</em></p>

<p><code>go
openwhisk.RegisterAction(func(value json.RawMessage) (interface{}, error) {
   ...  
}
</code></p>

<p>Re-writing the "reverse string" Action above to use this package is shown here.</p>

<p>``` go
package main</p>

<p>import (</p>

<pre><code>"encoding/json"
"github.com/jthomas/ow"
</code></pre>

<p>)</p>

<p>type Params struct {</p>

<pre><code>Payload string `json:"payload"`
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>type Result struct {</p>

<pre><code>Reversed string `json:"reversed"`
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>func reverse_string(to_reverse string) string {</p>

<pre><code>chars := []rune(to_reverse)
for i, j := 0, len(chars)-1; i &lt; j; i, j = i+1, j-1 {
    chars[i], chars[j] = chars[j], chars[i]
}
return string(chars)
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>func main() {</p>

<pre><code>ow.RegisterAction(func(value json.RawMessage) (interface{}, error) {
    var params Params
    err := json.Unmarshal(value, &amp;params)
    if err != nil {
        return nil, err
    }
    return Result{Reversed: reverse_string(params.Payload)}, nil
})
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Cross-compiling the Action source, bundling this package, creates a single
lightweight binary.</p>

<p>Embedding this file within a Docker image, using a minimal base image, creates
a tiny image (&lt;10MB). Containers from these images only execute a single
process to handle both the HTTP requests and running the Action source.</p>

<p><code>
FROM alpine:3.4
COPY action /action
EXPOSE 8080
CMD ["./action"]
</code></p>

<p>Pushing the local image to Dockerhub and then using it to create an Action
follows the same instructions above.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Running OpenWhisk Actions from user-provided Docker images allows developers to
execute "serverless functions" using any language. This is a fantastic feature
not currently supported by many of the other serverless providers.</p>

<p>OpenWhisk provides an
<a href="https://github.com/openwhisk/openwhisk/tree/master/sdk/docker">SDK</a> letting
users build a local Docker image which executes their Action and handles the
HTTP requests from the platform. Using this with <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_go_action/tree/master/docker_sdk">Go-based Actions</a> requires us
to cross-compile our binary for the platform and handle passing JSON through
command-line arguments and stdout.</p>

<p>Re-writing the HTTP handler <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_go_action/tree/master/go_handler">natively in Go</a>
means the Docker image can contain and execute a single binary for both tasks.
Using this <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/ow">Go package</a> provides an interface for registering Actions and handles
the HTTP requests automatically.</p>

<p><strong>This <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/openwhisk_go_action">project</a> contains
examples for the "reverse string" Action using both the Docker SDK and Go-based
handler detailed above.</strong></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
