<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: mvc | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/categories/mvc/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jamesthom.as/"/>
  <updated>2016-09-26T15:56:25+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jamesthom.as/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Part 3: Controllers]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/05/26/dojomvc-controllers/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-26T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/05/26/dojomvc-controllers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the final article of this series, we'll be looking at creating an MVC Controller for our sample todo
application.</p>

<p>We've already shown how to <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/02/26/dojomvc-models/">define our application model</a>,
creating a domain-specific todo model
backed by localStorage, along with <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/04/13/dojomvc-views/">our view template</a>,
using widget templating to render our tasks into the page.</p>

<p>{% blockquote Model View Controller Pattern http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93controller Wikipedia %}
The controller translates user input into operations on the model.
{% endblockquote %}</p>

<p>For our application, we need to handle the user actions to allow adding, removing and completing tasks. We already have a binding between a task's completed state
and our View, using the <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/architecture-examples/dojo/js/todo/form/CheckBox.js">todo.form.CheckBox</a>, allowing changes to flow back to the model without explicitly needing logic in the controller.</p>

<p>Let's look more closely at the remaining tasks...</p>

<h2>Adding Tasks</h2>

<p>The View template, discussed in the <a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/04/13/dojomvc-views/">second article</a>,
renders the HTML elements needed to allow the user to any new tasks. Once a user has finished
typing in their new task, signalled by pressing the enter key, we need to retrieve their text and add it to the model.</p>

<p>Using Dojo's <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dijit/_TemplatedMixin.html#dijit-templatedmixin">declarative programming model</a>,
the View template includes the custom element attribute needed to connect the "onkeypress" DOM event to an event handler within our controller. When our
widget is rendered in the page, by the Dojo parser, those connections are created automatically.</p>

<p><code>html Declarative event handling https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/architecture-examples/dojo/js/todo/app.html#L4 Source Link
&lt;input id="new-todo" data-dojo-attach-event="onkeypress:onKeyPress"
 placeholder="What needs to be done?" type="text" autofocus&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Inside our controller, each time an event is fired, the following function is executed:</p>

<p>``` javascript Controller event handler https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/architecture-examples/dojo/js/todo/app.js#L144-150 Source Link
onKeyPress: function (event) {</p>

<pre><code>if (event.keyCode !== keys.ENTER) return;

this.addToModel(event.target.value, false);
event.target.value = "";
dojo_event.stop(event);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Unless the user has pressed the enter key, we ignore the normal user input event. Once this happens, we extract the new
task text from the event argument and call the following convenience function to create the new task in the model.</p>

<p>``` javascript New model task https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/architecture-examples/dojo/js/todo/app.js#L144-150 Source Link
addToModel: function (content, isDone) {</p>

<pre><code>var insert = mvc.newStatefulModel({
    data: {todo_text: content, isDone: isDone}
});

this.model.todos.add(this.model.todos.length, insert);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>This function creates a new Model node, containing the task text and its
completed state, adding the result to the list of tasks. When inserting new
entries into the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html">DojoX MVC Model</a> array, the insertion position must be
specified explicitly. By using the current length of the list as the position,
we always add new items at the end.</p>

<p>Once the model has been modified, the View will automatically update to display the new item. We don't need to manually
update the rendered HTML template or even trigger re-loading of the View. By using widgets from the DojoX MVC package, changes to
the Model are always reflected in our View in real-time.</p>

<h2>Removing Tasks</h2>

<p>Removing tasks begins with the user clicking the destroy icon, displayed on the right-hand side of each task. Once this happens, the Controller
needs to trap the event, figure out which task to remove and update the Model. As the tasks' list
can be updated during the application, having an individual event connection for each task would require handling the setting up and tearing down
every time the list changed.</p>

<p>Instead, we can use "Event Delegation", introduced by the new Dojo event module, <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojo/on.html">dojo/on</a>,
to listen for any remove events with a single connection.</p>

<p>Once the widget has been rendered, signalled by the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dijit/_WidgetBase.html#lifecycle">"postCreate"</a>
function being called, we start listening for all click events on the destroy icons. Any events captured are passed through to our event hander, "onRemove", to delete the associated task from the Model.</p>

<p>``` javascript Event Delegation https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/architecture-examples/dojo/js/todo/app.js#L61-64 Source Link
postCreate: function () {</p>

<pre><code>on(this.domNode, ".destroy:click", lang.hitch(this, "onRemove"));
this.onItemStatusUpdate();
</code></pre>

<p>},</p>

<p>onRemove: function (event) {</p>

<pre><code>this.model.todos.remove(domAttr.get(event.target, "data-model-id"));
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>With one event handler for all the remove events, the Controller won't directly know which task within the Model the user
has chosen to remove. To overcome this, the repeating View template for the task uses a HTML5 data attribute to store the unique task index
on the rendered DOM element for the remove icon.</p>

<p>During rendering of a <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Repeat.html">DojoX MVC Repeat widget</a>,
the "index" attribute on the instance refers to the current
position within the bound list. This index value can then easily be retrieved from the event generated and used to remove the correct task from the Model.</p>

<p><code>html
&lt;button class="destroy" data-model-id="#{this.index}"&gt;
&lt;/button&gt;
</code></p>

<p>Once again, when the Model is changed, the View automatically updates. There's no action needed from the Controller in modifying the rendering HTML template.</p>

<h2>Clearing Completed Tasks</h2>

<p>Once a user has completed a series of tasks, they will eventually want to remove them. Rather than having to
remove each task individually, the application provides the ability to clear all completed tasks from the list.</p>

<p>Again, we've used declarative programming in the View template to connect our event hander, removeCompletedItems, to the DOM event
triggered when the user clicks the "Clear Completed" button.</p>

<p><code>html
&lt;button id="clear-completed" data-dojo-attach-event="onclick:removeCompletedItems"&gt;
&lt;/button&gt;
</code></p>

<p>When our handler is fired, we need to iterate over the existing tasks'
list, removing any with the correct completed state. Removing items from the Model will left-shift the remaining items, so we need to
take care to iterate correctly over the remaining items.</p>

<p>``` javascript Clearing Completed Items https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/architecture-examples/dojo/js/todo/app.js#L80-97 Source Link
removeCompletedItems: function () {</p>

<pre><code>var len = this.model.todos.length, idx = 0;

while (idx &lt; len) {
    if (this.model.todos[idx].isDone.value) {
        this.model.todos.remove(idx);
        len--;
        continue;
    }
    idx++;
}
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>When the event handler has finished executing, the View will be updated to clear out those completed tasks.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>In the final part of this series, we've looked at how to define an MVC
Controller, responsible for mediating between user actions and model
operations. Using declarative Dojo programming in our View template, we set up
bindings between DOM events and event handlers in our Controller.</p>

<p>When user
actions triggered those events, our handlers were responsible for adding and
removing todo tasks from the MVC Model class, StatefulModel, we've been using
to store our application data. These changes then flowed back to the View,
which automatically re-renders when it detects an updated Model.</p>

<p>Dojo's new MVC package, dojox.mvc, offers great capabilities for building dynamic
JavaScript applications using the MVC programming pattern. Although it's still maturing, hopefully this series
has been able to demonstrate that for most applications it's more than capable of providing the features
developers expect in a modern JavaScript MVC library.</p>

<p>If you have any further questions, feel free to leave comments below, send me an email or a tweet. The source
code for the application is available on Github, allowing you to run the examples above and compare it against other frameworks.</p>

<h3>What's Next?</h3>

<p>This series of articles was based upon the version of DojoX MVC present in the 1.7.0 release of The Dojo Toolkit. My experiences, good and bad,
building this application were <a href="http://mail.dojotoolkit.org/pipermail/dojo-contributors/2012-January/026434.html">fed back into the community</a> to
help improve the package in the future. With the upcoming 1.8 release of The Dojo Toolkit,
there has been some <a href="http://mail.dojotoolkit.org/pipermail/dojo-contributors/2012-February/026811.html">major improvements</a> to the MVC package, resolving many of the issues I raised.</p>

<p>When that version of the toolkit is available, I'll re-visit the application and show how those changes would make writing this application even simpler.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Part 2: Views]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/04/13/dojomvc-views/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-13T00:00:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/04/13/dojomvc-views</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In the previous article, we looked at defining our application Model using the
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc.html">Dojo MVC</a> package. The
model contained a list of todo tasks, each with a description and finished
state, along with composite values representing the total completed and
remaining task counts.</p>

<p>Dojo's MVC package provides a series of widgets (<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Group.html">Group</a>, <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Output.html">Output</a>, <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Repeat.html">Repeat</a>,
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Generate.html">Generate</a>) that assist the rendering of model attributes in our View, which
automatically update when model values change. We're going to look at using
these widgets to build our TodoMVC Application View...</p>

<h2>Defining a View template</h2>

<p>For a long time, Dojo has had excellent support for creating widgets with HTML
templates using modules from the Dijit package. Defining a new widget simply
requires inheriting from a base class (<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dijit/_WidgetBase.html">_WidgetBase</a>), adding in mixins for
template support (<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dijit/_TemplatedMixin.html">_TemplatedMixin</a> &amp; <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dijit/_WidgetsInTemplateMixin.html">_WidgetsInTemplateMixin</a>) and providing
a HTML template file that will be automatically rendered in the page by the Dojo
parser. In our application, we've created a new templated widget <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/tree/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo">todo.app</a>,
present in <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/app.js">app.js</a> along with a template file <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/app.html">app.html</a>.</p>

<p>The basic outline of this module is shown below.</p>

<p>``` javascript Templated TodoMVC Widget https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/app.js Source Link
define(["dojo/_base/declare",</p>

<pre><code>    // Parent classes
    "dijit/_WidgetBase", "dijit/_TemplatedMixin", "dijit/_WidgetsInTemplateMixin",
    // Widget template
    "dojo/text!./app.html",
    ...
function(declare, _WidgetBase, _TemplatedMixin, _WidgetsInTemplateMixin, template) {
    return declare("todo.app", [_WidgetBase, _TemplatedMixin, _WidgetsInTemplateMixin], {
        templateString: template,
    });
}
</code></pre>

<p>);
```</p>

<p>Defining our application as a templated widget lets us annotate HTML elements,
using the data-dojo-type attribute, in the application page to be automatically
instantiated into corresponding widgets at runtime by the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojo/parser.html">Dojo parser</a>. When this
occurs, the view template will replace the annotated HTML element in the page
and any child widgets in the view will be recursively created.</p>

<p>The HTML snippet below shows how we load Dojo, the parser, our application and turn on the automatic parsing on load to render
our Todo widget within the page.</p>

<p>``` html Loading TodoMVC App Within The Page https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/index.html Source Link</p>

<script data-dojo-config="async:true, parseOnLoad:true, paths:{'todo':'../../todo'}, 
    deps:['dojo/parser', 'todo/app']" src="./js/dtk/dojo/dojo.js"></script>


<p>...</p>

<div class="content" data-dojo-type="todo.app"></div>


<p>```</p>

<p>This templated widget is rendered within the page and represents our view. The view has three main
tasks:</p>

<p>** Display the list of todo items
* Allow a user to enter more tasks
* Show statistics for the number of completed and remaining tasks.</p>

<p>We'll look at each individually to see how we implemented those features using
the Dojo MVC package.</p>

<h2>Displaying Todo Tasks</h2>

<p>We've used the &lt;ul&gt; element to represent the container for our todo tasks, each task being an &lt;li&gt; element
with the same HTML template populated with different values. The content for each task and the number of tasks
needs to be dynamically generated based upon the values in the model.</p>

<p>Dojo MVC provides a widget for this pattern, <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Repeat.html">dojox.mvc.Repeat</a>,
letting the user specify an array in the model for binding to with a HTML
template to be repeated for each element.</p>

<p>The HTML template for the repeating todo tasks is shown below.</p>

<p>``` html Rendering Todo Tasks https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/app.html#L7-20 Source Link</p>

<ul class="todo-list" data-dojo-attach-point="todo_list" data-dojo-type="dojox.mvc.Repeat" data-dojo-props="ref: this.model.todos, exprchar: '#'">
    <li data-dojo-type="dojox.mvc.Group" data-dojo-props="ref: '#{this.index}'">
        <div class="todo">
            <input class="check" data-dojo-type="todo.form.CheckBox" data-dojo-props='ref: "isDone"'>
            <div class="todo-content dijitInline" data-dojo-type="dijit.InlineEditBox"
                data-dojo-props='ref: "todo_text", editor:"dijit.form.TextBox", autosave:true, width:"420px", style:"width:420px;"'></div>
            <span class="todo-destroy" data-model-id="#{this.index}">
            </span>
        </div>
    </li>
</ul>


<p>```</p>

<h3>Repeating View Templates</h3>

<p>In the template, the containing &lt;ul&gt; element is registered as the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Repeat.html">dojox.mvc.Repeat</a>
widget using the data-dojo-type attribute. Using the data-dojo-props
attribute, we can pass widget parameters to the newly created widget when it's instantiated by the parser.</p>

<p>The first parameter, ref, provides a variable name
for the model attribute to bind to. We're using the model available on the widget instance, "this.model", with the "todos" attribute, which contains
an array of task objects. The second parameter, exprchar, is the character to use for substitution expressions in declarative child widget attributes. By default,
this value is the '$' character. As we're using the declarative programming style, these expressions would be confused with normal template value substitutions and we
use the '#' character instead.</p>

<p>Under the &lt;ul&gt; element, we have the HTML template for each todo task, represented by the &lt;li&gt; element. Here we are using the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Group.html">dojox.mvc.Group</a> widget, which provides
the parent model context for any child widgets which use substituion expressions and references to access model values. Registering the parent context as an individual
item within the model "todos" array is achieved by using the "#{this.index}" reference, this will be automatically incremented by the parent Repeat widget as it iterates
through the model array.</p>

<h3>Binding UI Controls</h3>

<p>Each todo task has three UI controls, the task text (either as a read-only
value or an inline edit box for modification), a checkbox representing the
completed state of the widget and an icon to allow the removal of the task. Our
chosen UI controls (<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dijit/InlineEditBox.html">InlineEditBox</a> &amp; <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dijit/form/CheckBox.html">CheckBox</a>) are bound to model values by
providing a "ref" attribute with the attribute name. These widgets will
automatically be populated with the current model values during rendering.</p>

<p>This binding between the view and the model is bi-directional, changes to the
model will automatically propagate to the view widgets and changes to the view
widgets will flow back to the model.</p>

<p>When a user wants to remove a task, the "click" event generated by the icon in the view
will be intercepted by the Controller. Allowing the controller to determine which todo task
to remove from the model is provided by setting the current item index as a custom parameter on the HTML
element. We will be looking at the code to perform the removal in a later article.</p>

<h2>Showing Completed &amp; Remaining Counts</h2>

<p>Along with the todo tasks, we need to display stats for the number of completed
and remaining tasks. These attributes are composite model values, being
automatically calculated from other model attributes. The displayed values need
to be updated live as the other model attributes change but won't be directly
modifable by the user. The code snippet below shows the HTML template in the
view for this component.</p>

<p>``` html Showing Task Stats https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/app.html#L22-33 Source Link</p>

<div class="todo-stats" data-dojo-attach-point="todo_stats">
    <span class="todo-count">
        <span data-dojo-type="dojox.mvc.Output" data-dojo-props="ref: this.model.incomplete" class="number"></span>
        <span class="word">items</span> left.
    </span>
    <span class="todo-clear">
        <a href="#" data-dojo-attach-event="onclick:removeCompletedItems">
            Clear 
            <span class="number-done" data-dojo-type="dojox.mvc.Output" data-dojo-props="ref: this.model.complete" ></span>
            completed items
        </a>
    </span>
</div>


<p>```</p>

<p>We've used simple HTML elements to display the values, rather than Dijit widgets, due to the
lack of user interaction needed. Binding a HTML element to a Model property can be achieved using the
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/1.7/dojox/mvc/Output.html">dojox.mvc.Output</a> widget.
Again, we use the "ref" attribute to specify which model property the "innerHTML"
value on the HTML element should be linked with.</p>

<h2>Adding New Tasks</h2>

<p>Finally, we need to let the user add new tasks. Using a normal HTML input
field, we connect the "onkeypress" event to an internal event handler to allow
the app to access the new tasks.</p>

<p>``` html Adding New Tasks https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/blob/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/app.html#L2-5 Source Link</p>

<div class="create-todo">
    <input class="new-todo" data-dojo-attach-event="onkeypress:onKeyPress" placeholder="What needs to be done?" type="text"/>
    <span class="ui-tooltip-top" style="display:none;">Press Enter to save this task</span>
</div>


<p>```</p>

<p>The application controller is responsible for
handling the generated events, retrieving the new tasks and adding them into
the model. We'll be looking at exactly how this works in the next article. When
new tasks are added, the task list in the view will be automatically
re-rendered.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>Following on from the first article, we've now looked at how the View component
of our MVC application works. Using Dojo MVC widgets, we've been able to
bind simple HTML elements and full Dijit widgets to show model values. This
dynamic binding allows Model updates to automatically flow through to the View controls.
Secondly, any user modified values automatically update the Model.</p>

<p>The dojox.mvc.Output widget was used to display Model attributes are
read-only values in normal HTML elements. We also used the dojox.mvc.Repeat
and dojox.mvc.Group widgets to generate a repeated view template for the
todo tasks. Connecting user events from the view to the Controller used Dojo's
templated widget mixins.</p>

<p>In the final article, we'll look at the last component the MVC pattern,
Controllers. This includes adding new tasks to the Model, removing individual
and completed tasks along with controlling the view components being displayed.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Part 1: Models]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/02/26/dojomvc-models/"/>
    <updated>2012-02-26T10:33:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/02/26/dojomvc-models</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In this first article, we going to look at using <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc.html">DojoX MVC</a> to define our
application Models, showing the use of the new <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html">StatefulModel</a> class. Later in
the series, we'll look at binding our defined Model to a View template, rendering
the HTML output and hooking into user events.</p>

<h2>Introducing StatefulModels</h2>

<p><a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc.html">DojoX MVC</a> uses a specific class for representing Models in the MVC pattern,
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html">StatefulModel</a>. By using or extending this class, applications have access to a
native JavaScript data model that integrates with all the classes under the MVC
package. StatefulModel extends the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojo/Stateful.html">Dojo Stateful</a> class, introduced in Dojo 1.6
to provide a way to monitor widget property changes, to support more complex
behaviour, such as binding to and updating View component, validating of model
values and much more.</p>

<p>StatefulModels are instantiated from a plain JavaScript object, representing the initial data structure
for the model, or even from a Dojo Store (with support for both synchronous and asynchronous results). To assist the conversion of complex JavaScript objects, a factory function is provided
that will traverse the source data, recursively converting all data properties to use the
StatefulModel class.</p>

<p>Further details on the StatefulModel class can be found <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html#dojox-mvc-statefulmodel">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Defining a Model</h2>

<p>Reviewing the <a href="https://github.com/addyosmani/todomvc/wiki/Todo-Application-Specification">TodoMVC specification</a>,
our application Model needs to contain a list of todo tasks, each one
containing a description and that task's completed state. The task's
description will be provided by the user and can later be modified. As the task
is completed, the task's internal state must be updated. Representing the todo
tasks as an array of objects will allow binding to a <a href="http://livedocs.dojotoolkit.org/dojox/mvc/Repeat">Repeat View</a>, having a HTML template
rendered for each task in the Model.</p>

<p>Looking at the application, there's two additional properties in the View that are derived from
other Model attributes, counts for the completed and remaining tasks. To allow automatic binding of these
values into our View template, we're going to represent these directly in our model. Later on, we'll
set up binding between Model values to allow those composite values to be calculated automatically.</p>

<p>``` javascript
var data = {</p>

<pre><code>todos: [
    {
        text: "Must write this blog article"
        isDone: false
    }
],
remaining: 0,
complete: 0
</code></pre>

<p>}</p>

<p>var model = dojox.mvc.newStatefulModel({data: data})
```</p>

<p>Once we've defined our Model as a native JavaScript object, we can use the
StatefulModel factory to perform the conversion to StatefulModel classes, as
shown in the sample above. The result of this function is our application
Model, which we can then bind to our View and interact with via the Controller.</p>

<p>The StatefulModel class supports any native JavaScript type, we're using
strings for the description, booleans for the completed state and numbers for
the computed totals.</p>

<h2>Binding to Model changes</h2>

<p>Once you've defined a model, you'll want to be notified of any attribute changes.
Using Dojo Stateful's <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojo/Stateful.html#watch">"watch"</a> method, we can register a function to be executed
whenever that model's attributes are modified using the getter &amp; setter pattern.</p>

<p><code>javascript
model.watch("attribute", function (attribute, new_value, old_value) {
});
</code></p>

<p>The <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/Bind.html">dojox.mvc.Bind</a> module extends this functionality to cover two common patterns,
listening to changes on a series of attributes and binding model properties together.
The "bindInputs" function allows an array of model attributes to be passed in, executing a callback
whenever any of the attributes change.</p>

<p><code>javascript
mvc.bindInputs([model.first_attr, model.second_attr, ...], function (attribute, new_value, old_value) {
});
</code></p>

<p>More usefully, the "bind" function sets up a one way coupling between a source and destination model attribute.
Whenever the source attribute value changes, the destination model attribute will be automatically updated with
the same result. If you want to transform the source value before it's updated in the destination model, an optional
function callback can be passed in. This will be called with the new attribute
value and the return value used to update the destination model.</p>

<p>``` javascript
mvc.bind(source_model, "attr", dest_model, "attr", function (attribute, new_value, old_value) {</p>

<pre><code>// Return transformed value to update dest_model with
</code></pre>

<p>});
```</p>

<h2>Creating composite model values</h2>

<p>In the TodoMVC application our model has two attributes, "remaining" &amp; "completed", that need to computed
automatically from other model values.</p>

<p>Calculating the "completed" total is performed by looping through the "todos" array and counting
the tasks which have an "isDone" attribute as true. Whenever a task's "isDone" value changes
we want to re-calculate and update the "completed" total. Whenever a new task is added, we
automatically bind the new item to our calculating function, which updates the composite value
with the new count if any of our model tasks are modified.</p>

<p>``` javascript
bindIsDone: function (item) {</p>

<pre><code>mvc.bindInputs([item.isDone], lang.hitch(this, "updateTotalItemsLeft"));
</code></pre>

<p>},</p>

<p>updateTotalItemsLeft: function () {</p>

<pre><code>this.remaining.set("value", array.filter(this.todos, function (item) {
    return item &amp;&amp; !item.isDone.value;
}).length);
</code></pre>

<p>}
```</p>

<p>Once we have the "completed" total, the "remaining" attribute can be easily calculated
if we know the total number of tasks. Using the "bind" method ensures this happens automatically,
using optional transform function to create the new composite value.</p>

<p>``` javascript
mvc.bind(this.remaining, "value", this.complete, "value", lang.hitch(this, function (value) {</p>

<pre><code>return this.todos.get("length") - value;
</code></pre>

<p>}));
```</p>

<h2>Extending StatefulModel</h2>

<p>Defining our Model requires application code to declare the composite (completed, remaining) attributes, bind to changes on the
current (and future) todo tasks and deal with persisting data to local storage. Rather than having this code in the application
controller, we can extend the StatefulModel class to encapsulate all this
logic. Using Dojo's <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojo/declare.html">Declare</a> module, we can create a new
class which extends StatefulModel, allowing us to set the initial model properties as class attributes rather than having to call
the dojox.mvc.newStatefulModel() factory manually. The skeleton outline for our StatefulModel extension is shown below, we've removed
some internal methods for brevity.</p>

<p>``` javascript
define(["dojo/_base/declare", "dojox/mvc/StatefulModel", "todo/store/LocalStorage", "dojox/mvc"],</p>

<pre><code>function(declare, StatefulModel, LocalStorage, mvc) {

return declare([StatefulModel], {
    data: {
        id: "local_storage_todos",
        todos : [],
        remaining: 0,
        complete: 0
    },

    store: new LocalStorage(),

    constructor: function () {
        var data = this.store.get(this.data.id) || this.data;
        this._createModel(data);

        this.setUpModelBinding();
        this.updateTotalItemsLeft();
    },

    setUpModelBinding: function () {
        mvc.bind(this.incomplete, "value", this.complete, "value", lang.hitch(this, function (value) {
            return this.todos.get("length") - value;
        }));
        array.forEach(this.todos, lang.hitch(this, "bindIsDone"));
        this.todos.watch(lang.hitch(this, "onTodosModelChange"));
    },

    updateTotalItemsLeft: function () {
        this.incomplete.set("value", array.filter(this.todos, function (item) {
            return item &amp;&amp; !item.isDone.value;
        }).length);
    }
});
</code></pre>

<p>);
```</p>

<p>The internal "data" and "store" attributes correspond to properties on the base
StatefulModel class. StatefulModel's constructor will automatically transform raw
JavaScript objects, set via the "data" property, into the corresponding
StatefulModels.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, it doesn't contain code for automatically
populating the initial model from the "store" property, this is handled in the
"dojox.mvc.newStatefulModel" factory. Therefore, we manually construct the
initial model values from the store, if available, and re-call the "_createModel" function
in our constructor.</p>

<p>Once the model has been instantiated, we can declare and initialise our composite model bindings
as well as binding to the initial todo tasks pulled from persistent storage.</p>

<p>You can see the source code for the final version of the TodoModel class
<a href="https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc/tree/master/todo-example/dojo/js/todo/model">here</a>.</p>

<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>In this first article, we've reviewed how to use DojoX MVC's StatefulModel
class to create application Models that we can later bind to Views within the
application. Using the StatefulModel class, we can bind to model properties,
having callbacks executed when one or more attribute values changed.</p>

<p>Taking this further, we can bind model properties together, creating dynamic
models whose properties automatically update as others change. Combining this
functionality, we defined composite model attributes for the "completed" and
"remaining" properties that were automatically calculated as the todo tasks'
state changed, wrapping this code within an extension of the StatefulModel
class.</p>

<p>Next time, we'll be looking at another component of the MVC pattern, Views. Using the TodoMVC application
as our example, we'll show how to define View templates, bind our Model with the View to generate the application's HTML and
ensure user interactions with the todo tasks automatically update the Model.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Creating Todo MVC in Dojo - Overview]]></title>
    <link href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/01/28/dojomvc_overview/"/>
    <updated>2012-01-28T21:10:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/01/28/dojomvc_overview</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before Christmas, <a href="http://addyosmani.com/blog/">Addy Osmani</a>
sent out the following
tweet asking for a Dojo-version of the TodoMVC application.</p>

<blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p>
Quick updates: Added ExtJS and MVC-less Todo apps to the current dev version of TodoMVC. Want to get a Dojo version in there before 0.3.
</p>&mdash; Addy Osmani (@addy_osmani) <a
href="https://twitter.com/addy_osmani/status/134641372367032321"
data-datetime="2011-11-10T20:21:07+00:00">November10, 2011</a></blockquote>


<script src="http://jamesthom.as//platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charset="utf-8"></script>


<p></p>

<p>Reviewing their <a href="https://github.com/addyosmani/todomvc">Github page</a>, the
project aims to allow developers to compare MVC frameworks by providing
implementations of a sample Todo application using different toolkit's MVC
support. They currently have over a <a href="http://addyosmani.github.com/todomvc/">dozen entries</a> for toolkits, including
Backbone, JavascriptMVC and Spine with more coming soon but, unfortunately, no
entry for The Dojo Toolkit.</p>

<h2>Introducing DojoX MVC</h2>

<p>With the 1.6 release, The Dojo Toolkit introduced a new DojoX module that
experimented with <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc.html">better MVC support</a>, utilising
recent features that provide automatic
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html#dojox-mvc-statefulmodel">widget property</a>
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/features/1.6/widget-watch">monitoring</a>.
The module goes beyond simple data binding between models and views, including <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/Generate.html#dojox-mvc-generate">mapping model attributes to appropriate UI controls</a>, <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html#dojox-mvc-statefulmodel">model data validation</a>,
<a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc/StatefulModel.html#dojox-mvc-statefulmodel">data store integration</a>
and others. Further improvements were introduced in the recent 1.7 release of
The Dojo Toolkit and it is still under active development. For full details on DojoX MVC, see the <a href="http://dojotoolkit.org/reference-guide/dojox/mvc.html">reference guide</a>.</p>

<p>I've been wanting to play with this module for a while and taking up Addy's
challenge provided an ideal opportunity. With help from <a href="https://github.com/edchat">Ed Chatelain</a> and others,
we created and refined our entry over the past two months, ready in time for
the 0.3 release of the project.</p>

<p>Being a new part of the toolkit, there weren't many examples of using the module for building
non-trivial applications. Dojo's TodoMVC entry should provide a good starting point for developers who
want to explore DojoX MVC and compare its approach to other toolkits.</p>

<h2>Walk-through series</h2>

<p>Over the coming weeks, I'm going to walk-through building of the TodoMVC
application using DojoX MVC in a series of articles. It will cover defining a
model with composite attributes, generating views from the model, binding user
actions to model attributes and using local storage for persisting items
offline. I'll also cover some common issues that developers might encounter
when using the module.</p>

<p><del>Check back soon for the first part....</del></p>

<h3><em>Update (26/05/12)</em></h3>

<p><em>All articles are now available and the links are below...</em></p>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/02/26/dojomvc-models/">Part One: Models</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/04/13/dojomvc-views/">Part Two: Views</a></li>
<li><a href="http://jamesthom.as/blog/2012/05/26/dojomvc-controllers/">Part Three: Controllers</a></li>
</ul>


<h2>Can't wait?</h2>

<p>If you want to dive straight in, the finished application is in my <a href="https://github.com/jthomas/todomvc">fork of the TodoMVC project</a>, under the "todo-example/dojo" directory.
The entry's <a href="https://github.com/addyosmani/todomvc/pull/54">pull request</a> has a good discussion about issues encountered, re-factoring, enhancements, etc.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
