<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: presentations | James Thomas]]></title>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/categories/presentations/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/"/>
  <updated>2015-07-01T16:36:29+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[James Thomas]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[London JS - Watson]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2012/10/22/london-js/"/>
    <updated>2012-10-22T16:43:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2012/10/22/london-js</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last month, I was invited to speak at LondonJS on the machine learning and artificial intelligence behind IBM Watson.</p>

<p>I jokingly said the talk would win the prize for the "least amount of JavaScript-related content in a LondonJS talk".</p>

<p>The idea was to introduce the audience to topics (machine learning) that might be relevant in the future and IBM Watson was a
great example that people love hearing about.</p>

<p>Slides for the event are now posted online, check them out <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/u/jthomas/p/a-computer-called-watson">here</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[IBM IMPACT 2012 - Session Materials Available]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2012/05/08/impact-slides-available/"/>
    <updated>2012-05-08T15:28:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2012/05/08/impact-slides-available</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week was IBM IMPACT 2012, IBM's premier conference for our customers in Las Vegas. I was fortunate enough to
be there for the duration, presentating four sessions on The Dojo Toolkit. The whole event was a fantastic showcase
for our company, the capabilities and unique values we provide. Session materials from my talks are now available
<a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/jthomas">externally</a>, see below for individual links.</p>

<h3>IBM IMPACT Sessions</h3>

<ul>
<li><a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/jthomas/p/optimising-your-dojo-application-using-the-dojo-build-system">Optimizing Your Dojo Application Using The Dojo Build System</a></li>
<li><a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/jthomas/p/moving-to-dojo-17-and-the-path-to-20">Moving to Dojo 1.7 and the Path to 2.0</a></li>
<li><a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/jthomas/p/beyond-dojo-the-rise-of-asynchronous-module-definition-amd">Beyond Dojo: The Rise of Advanced Micro Devices (AMD)</a></li>
<li><a href="http://speakerdeck.com/u/jthomas/p/javascript-anti-patterns-moving-from-java-to-javascript">Unconference Session: JavaScript Anti-Patterns (Moving from Java to JavaScript)</a></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Upcoming Talks]]></title>
    <link href="http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2012/04/13/upcoming-talks/"/>
    <updated>2012-04-13T18:45:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://jthomas.github.com/jthomas/blog/2012/04/13/upcoming-talks</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Next month I'll be presenting at <a href="http://www-01.ibm.com/software/websphere/events/impact/">IBM IMPACT 2012</a>, IBM's premier
customer conference in Las Vegas from April 29th until May 4th. I've had three
sessions accepted, full details below.  If you're attending the conference and
want to say hello, please let me know.</p>

<p>This week I was invited to present a preview of the joint session I'm doing with
<a href="https://twitter.com/#!/dylans">Dylan Schiemann</a> at IMPACT for <a href="http://londonajax.com/">London AJAX</a>. There
was a really great crowd of over seventy developers waiting to hear all about AMD. The talk was recorded and can
now be viewed online <a href="http://skillsmatter.com/podcast/ajax-ria/amd-depth">here</a>. Due to an unexpected travel delay
I was delayed by 30 minutes, you can see my appearance after that. Thanks for Dylan for carrying the show until I
arrived!</p>

<p>During this year's IBM IMPACT conference, there's an official "unconference" running on the Wendesday. Anyone can submit
ideas for talks, from full sessions to lightning talks, with the community voting on what they would like to see. I've submitted
an idea for a lightning talk titled "<a href="http://websphere.uservoice.com/forums/100171-websphere-unconference/suggestions/2672597-javascript-anti-patterns-moving-from-java-to-jav">JavaScript Anti-Patterns - Moving from Java to JavaScript</a>". If you want to see this talk, visit
the link and vote for the idea.</p>

<p>Once the conference has finished I'll make all of the material available externally.</p>

<p>See you all in Vegas!</p>

<h3>IBM IMPACT Schedule</h3>

<ul>
<li><p>TDW-2292: Optimizing Your Dojo Application Using The Dojo Build System</p>

<ul>
<li>Session Type:  Lecture</li>
<li>Date/Time:  Tue, 1/May, 03:15 PM - 04:30 PM</li>
<li>Room:  Venetian - Marcello 4401A</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>TDW-1537: Moving to Dojo 1.7 and the Path to 2.0</p>

<ul>
<li>Session Type:  Lecture</li>
<li>Date/Time:  Thu, 3/May, 10:30 AM - 11:45 AM</li>
<li>Room:  Venetian - Marcello 4402</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><p>TDW-2286: Beyond Dojo: The Rise of Asynchronous Module Definition (AMD)</p>

<ul>
<li>Session Type:  Lecture</li>
<li>Date/Time:  Thu, 3/May, 08:45 AM - 10:00 AM</li>
<li>Room:  Venetian - Marcello 4403</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
